<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse concerning the redeeming of time by Edward Pelling, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to Their Majesties, and rector of Petworth in Sussex.</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42376</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36273381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36273381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150153</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150153)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2234:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse concerning the redeeming of time by Edward Pelling, D.D. chaplain in ordinary to Their Majesties, and rector of Petworth in Sussex.</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>104, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCV [1695]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Imprimatur, Aug. 7. 1694. Carolus Alston."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [6]-[8] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Time --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Practical Diſcourſe CONCERNING <hi>The REDEEMING</hi> OF TIME.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to their Majeſties, and Rector of <hi>Petworth</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Aug.</hi> 7. 1694.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Carolus Alſton.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Everingham;</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> near the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul's.</hi> MDCXCV.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:5"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150153:5"/>
            <head>A Practical Diſcourſe Concerning the Redeeming of TIME.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What is meant by the Redeeming of Time, and the Reaſons for it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>ST. <hi>Paul</hi> in two ſeveral places directs us to <hi>Redeem Time, Epheſ.</hi> 5. 16. and <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 5. And that I may not, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny needleſs Preface, ſpend that which he thought ſo Precious, as to be worth all our endeavours to <hi>Redeem,</hi> I ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately pitch upon the conſideration of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150153:6"/>
the matter, and enquire into three neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is meant by Redeeming of Time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> How very Reaſonable our Duty is as to this particular.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How we may order the matter ſo, as to Redeem our Time to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> then; Some look upon this Phraſe, <hi>The Redeeming of Time,</hi> as a Proverbial Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; and underſtand by it, the uſing all Prudent and Honeſt ways to avoid pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Danger; By putting Danger off by Delays, and by <hi>Gaining of Time,</hi> as we are wont to ſpeak. And in this ſenſe the <hi>Greek Tranſlation of</hi> the <hi>Bible</hi> uſes the Phraſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 8. And <hi>Seneca</hi> hath an Expreſſion very like it to the ſame purpoſe <hi>(Epiſt.</hi> 13.)</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing this to be the immediate Scripture ſenſe of the Phraſe, it is not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent to underſtand it in the more Literal Conſtruction, and as it commonly ſounds in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for the Application of all poſſible Endeavours to make the beſt uſe of our Time we can. This Senſe is proper; and conſidering how Neceſſary the Practice of the thing is, I ſhall take the liberty to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it according to the uſual impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150153:6"/>
of the words, with due Submiſſion to the Judgment of ſome Learned Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Redeem,</hi> is to recover that which was once Loſt, and when we apply it to <hi>Time,</hi> it ſignifies the Recovering of thoſe Hours, which have been <hi>miſpent,</hi> and <hi>thrown away;</hi> by Labouring hard for the Future, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy every Minute we have to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Time is always</hi> in the <hi>Flux;</hi> nor can we have any preſent poſſeſſion, but of a moment. God gives us our Time, Minute by Minute; that we may be the better Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands of it; eſpecially conſidering that on every Moment an Eternity of Happineſs or Miſery doth depend; nor is it poſſible for us to Recover Yeſterday, ſo as to make that to be preſent again, which is actually Elapſed. The nature of the thing will not allow it: and yet it is poſſible to do it a <hi>Moral</hi> way; by making all the <hi>Compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> we can for what is gone, by the Intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Zeal, and by the <hi>multiplication</hi> of our <hi>good Actions;</hi> by adding in weight that which is wanting as to the number of our days; by rendring our ſelves doubly beneficial; as if we made one day, two, by improving the Preſent in Proportion ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and tantamount to what is gone. This is in Gods Account, a Revocation of our time; a <hi>Redemption of it;</hi> ſo as to make it our own again, by laying out an equivalent proportion of Induſtry and Labour, in lieu
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150153:7"/>
of thoſe Hours which have been either ſquandred away, or not half ſo well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, as they ought, and might have been.</p>
               <p>And this I take to be the ground of that Rule, by which our Saviour tells us, he will proceed, <hi>The Firſt ſhall be Laſt; and the Laſt, Firſt; or, the Firſt ſhall be as the Laſt; and the Laſt as the Firſt;</hi> Meaning, that tho' God is pleas'd to call ſome to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Goſpel much earlier than he doth others; yet many of thoſe who Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Faith later than the reſt, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an equal Reward with ſuch as Profeſs'd it ſooner. The reaſon is, becauſe theſe made up their Time by their Extraordinary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; they that go into the <hi>Vine-yard at the Laſt Call,</hi> may by the earneſtneſs and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of their Performances, deſerve as well, and do as much Work in a little time, as thoſe who have <hi>born the Heat and Burden of the Day,</hi> and yet did not work ſo hard, tho <hi>they went in at the Firſt Call.</hi> Hence Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Many are called, but few choſen;</hi> that is, tho many Profeſs the Truth, yet few in compariſon, make ſuch vaſt improvements of their Time, as by their Extraordinary Labours to render themſelves Eminent and Choice Servants of God. That extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Labourer, and moſt Zealous Apoſtle (St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I mean) <hi>was One of thoſe few.</hi> He ſaid indeed, <hi>That he was the Leaſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and leſs than the leaſt of all Saints, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150153:7"/>
that he was as one born out of due time,</hi> I Cor. 15. 8. But, though to ſhew his great <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> for his Sins, he ſpake ſo diſdainfully of himſelf, as if he were like an <hi>Abortive,</hi> that wanted thoſe perfect <hi>Proportions</hi> which a Child hath, that ſtayeth the full Courſe of Nature; yet he filled up his time by his <hi>unparallel'd Zeal and Vigour;</hi> nor doth all the <hi>Scripture,</hi> I think, give us ſuch another Inſtance, as he was, to ſhew what it is to <hi>Redeem the Time: I Labour'd,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>more abundantly than they All,</hi> I Cor. 15. 10. Theſe were not Vain, Boaſting Expreſſions, but a juſt acknowledgement of what he found himſelf Obliged to do to make God and Man all poſſible Reparation. He would not loſe an Hour more; but ſtrove to Expiate his Guilt for coming ſo late into the Church, and for waſting it ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Entrance.</p>
               <p>By this great <hi>Example of himſelf,</hi> which the penitent Apoſtle ſet to his own Advice, we may eaſily perceive what it is to <hi>Redeem the Time.</hi> He was ready to be at any coſt, to retrieve (what he could) thoſe fair Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of doing the World and himſelf <hi>good,</hi> which upon his melancholy Reflections, he ſaw were dropt out of his hands. Labour, Sufferings, Life it ſelf; All he thought lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough to make amends. So that to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem our time in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> way is, with all poſſible application and Earneſtneſs of mind to make the Beſt uſe we can of the Preſent;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150153:8"/>
to Increaſe our diligence every New day; as to employ the Remainder of our life with ſuch great care and husbandry, as if we were within a ſhort ſpace to dye, and to go to Judgment.</p>
               <p>And if people would but <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> conſider, how valuable time is, and what the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences will moſt certainly be, whether they Improve, or Throw it away, one would think no other Motive would be needful, to make them Husband it well, but this Single thought; that whatever they do, they are ſtill dealing for an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. It is the onely buſineſs we have in this world, to be evermore Regular and conſtant in the courſe God hath ſet us, as the Sun is in his motions. From the womb to the Grave we have our days numbred out unto us; or however we ſpend them, whether well, or ill, we may be ſure it will turn to ſome account: there is no medium, or Remedy, but we muſt be Infinitely <hi>Gainers or Loſers</hi> by it; this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all who believe a Future ſtate.</p>
               <p>However, that notions of this kind, may make the deeper impreſſion, 'twill be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in the proſecution of this ſubject to conſider diſtinctly theſe three things.</p>
               <p>1. Firſt, how very Prejudicial to the ſoul we find the Loſs of time to be already.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150153:8"/>
Secondly, how Irreparable the Loſs will be in another life.</p>
               <p>And Thirdly, how dangerous it is, in relation even to our preſent outward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. Theſe few things, if gravely and wiſely conſider'd, would naturally excite men to Redeem their time, while it is yet in their Power, and while the Price of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is as yet in their hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:150153:9"/>
               <head>CHAP II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How very prejudicial to the Soul Men may find the loſs of</hi> Time <hi>to be already.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> HOW very prejudicial to the Soul we find the loſs of <hi>Time</hi> to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. The Perfections of the <hi>Soul,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>Intellectual,</hi> or <hi>Moral,</hi> are not wrought by any ſudden inſtantaneous Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but are acquired by degrees; <hi>Knowledge,</hi> by Speculation and hard Studies; <hi>Virtue,</hi> by Practice, by many repeated Acts, which improve good Diſpoſitions into a ſetled ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of <hi>Living well;</hi> now this requires <hi>Time,</hi> and therefore the Scripture expreſſes it, by <hi>growing in Grace,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 18. becauſe thoſe gracious Diſpoſitions riſe and increaſe <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually.</hi> Though the <hi>Principle</hi> be <hi>Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> yet 'tis <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> that bringeth <hi>Fruit unto Perfection.</hi> A <hi>Muſbrome</hi> may be the work of a Night only, but ſubſtantial <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> being Acts of a Mans Will, governed by Arguments from <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> muſt needs be of ſlow growth; eſpecially ſo as to become cuſtomary and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150153:9"/>
habitual. Upon this account the loſs of <hi>Time</hi> is very ſenſibly prejudicial to Peoples <hi>Souls,</hi> becauſe thereby the buſineſs of their <hi>Salvation</hi> (in the Works whereof they ſhould have kept equal Paces with their <hi>Time,</hi> that great and urgent buſineſs) is put quite backward, and left behind-hand, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be fetch'd up again without <hi>double Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence</hi> at the leaſt. Their Underſtandings are darkened or deluded, for want of that true Information, which their Minds might have received, had they not ſlept or ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away many happy <hi>Oportunities,</hi> or ſpent them upon ſecular Concernments. Their Senſe of Religion is comparatively very ſuperficial, by their neglecting thoſe Hours which ſhould have been employed about it. Their <hi>Virtues</hi> are inconſiderable for want of Practice. Briefly, all thoſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements which others have made, and which are neceſſary for all, to prepare and fit their Souls for a <hi>bleſſed State</hi> hereafter, ſuch careleſs People are to ſeek for, and perhaps at laſt diſpair of making, when once they are throughly ſenſible of their Neglects, and find the Inconveniences of a ſick Bed, or the dulneſs of old Age to come upon them. Inſtead of thoſe Perfections in <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> Vice gets ground apace, every day it grows more and more habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; till in the end it is as hard a matter to reform thoſe who are accuſtomed to do E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, as it is to make an <hi>Ethiopian</hi> change his Skin, or a Leopard his Spots, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150153:10"/>
We ſhould therefore <hi>Redeem the Time,</hi> while poſſability and practicableneſs of the thing gives us Encouragements. We com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly look back upon our Loſſes with a ſadneſs, and with many diſquieting <hi>Thoughts:</hi> God knoweth, 'tis too often thus in our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Affairs, though it be natural enough, 'tis the ready way to create pain in the Heart of any unproſperous Man to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not only what Fortunes he hath actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>loſt,</hi> but what <hi>Advantages</hi> he has <hi>miſt</hi> too; what he might have come to, had he been diligent and wiſe; what he might have <hi>done;</hi> what he might have <hi>been;</hi> how many he might have out-ſtript in the World; how many ways he might have improved his Intereſt, had his Hands been Induſtrious, and had he not let ſo many fair <hi>Opportunities</hi> ſlip out of them. If any thing can ſpur up ſuch an improvident and reſtiff Creature, by vigorous Courſes to <hi>Redeem</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> that is gone from him, the Senſe of this muſt. And if Men were as heartily concern'd for <hi>Spiritual,</hi> as they are for theſe external, tranſitory Matters, they would hardly need any other Perſwaſions to <hi>Redeem their Time,</hi> but this ſingle Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>What Debtors they are to their own Souls; and what great Arrears they are in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves.</hi> Since they came into the World capable of any Impreſſions, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out the days of their Child hood in a State of perfect Innocence, (comparatively) What Proficients, in <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150153:10"/>
might they have been, by that time they came of Age, had they not dropt their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Time</hi> with their Trifles and Toys? And ſince they had the ſame equal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage with <hi>Timothy,</hi> of knowing the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> from their Child-hood, they might have been wiſe unto <hi>Salvation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too, had they ſpent their days in chewing over, and digeſting thoſe whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Doctrines, wherein <hi>Timothy</hi> was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be nouriſhed up, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 6. Many Vices might have been deſtroyed upon their firſt appearance, like <hi>Cockatrices</hi> cruſht in the Egg. <hi>Paſſion</hi> would have met with an early check. <hi>Meekneſs, Patience, Humility, Charity,</hi> and a <hi>devout Temper,</hi> would not have been ſcorn'd, as Phlegmatick and ungenerous Diſpoſitions. <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is now proſtituted to <hi>Luſt,</hi> would have have preſerved in a pure and undefiled State. Vaſt Improvements might have been made, had People but made a good uſe of their <hi>Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only way therefore they have now to Redeem it, is to recover of their Loſſes as much as they can; and that with all poſſible ſpeed; becauſe the longer this Care is deferred, the greater ſtill their Loſſes are; like Debts, which every day ſwell by being <hi>neglected.</hi> Wicked Habits grow daily, and are more and more confirmed by Pleaſure and Cuſtom, till the Ear becomes deaf, and the Heart hardned. There is a Succeſſion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150153:11"/>
of Follies, as there is of Years. When the <hi>Rattle</hi> is thrown away, <hi>Vanity</hi> is taken up; and <hi>Vice</hi> takes the next turn. Thus the <hi>Youth</hi> commenceth a Son of <hi>Belial;</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds by degrees from the Womb towards Hell; unleſs ſome ſurpriſing Judgments meet him in the way, to give him a ſtop, after many Prayers and Counſels of Friends that have been uſed in vain. By this courſe of Life, Vice is reckoned in the end one of the Accompliſhments of a Man; and when once it comes to be grave, to act with Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Deliberation, and Deſigns, it is infinitely harder to be conquered, then it was in the days of innocent Ignorance; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the hurt and miſchief which is done to the poor Soul by a long Trade of Wickedneſs, is inexpreſſible; and therefore Men ſhould Redeem their <hi>Time</hi> while they have it to Redeem, and while the thing is practicable; for the longer it runs, the more it will be out of their Power; their <hi>Time</hi> is ſtill leſs and leſs, yet their Vices increaſe and wax the ſtronger; and their Minds are every day the more ſtiff and inflexible; So that when old Age comes, there is a crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs within, which is far worſe then that in the Bones; and 'tis to be fear'd, that a Death bed Repentance is ſeldom genuine and ſincere, after a long Life of <hi>Impiety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes it happens, that inſtead of Repenting, People are ready to deſpair; believing that after ſo much Time quite
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150153:11"/>
miſ-ſpent, the poor remainder is too little, and too late for the beginning of a great Work, when ones courſe is now finiſhing. The thought of this is like an heavy Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, which a Man knows not how to bear up againſt. His Heart ſinks under the preſſure, and he gives over all Endeavors; becauſe he thinks no Labor or Means will be to purpoſe, eſpecially when <hi>Attempts</hi> have been altogether ineffectual and fruitleſs. This is a ſad conſequence of the loſs of <hi>Time,</hi> when it thus terminates in Horror and Dampneſs. And yet, though the thing be evil, the caſe is not uncommon; and conſidering the Danger that is ſo viſible before all negligent People, one would think the very fear of what may be, ſhould ſtir them up to make proviſion againſt Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, by well husbanding the Preſent. We may be ſure, the Remembrance of ſo much <hi>Time Loſt,</hi> muſt needs be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable in that day, when Mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are wont to ſpeak home and plain. Suppoſe ones Heart be truly Penitent, it cannot but afford him a very melancholy Proſpect, to look back upon his former Life, and to ſee what a long Courſe he has run to ſad purpoſe: How many fair Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing good have been baulk'd; how little Religion hath been minded (tho' it be the great thing for which we were all brought into the World;) How many Motions of Gods <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted; How many <hi>Mercies</hi> have been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150153:12"/>
How often private Affairs have been preferred to the <hi>Divine Service;</hi> How many hours have been trifled away, which ſhould have been imployed at Gods Houſe; How many Sins have been acted, when the Works of <hi>Salvation</hi> ſhould, and might have been look'd after; in ſhort, how Vice and Vanity, and Idleneſs have divided that Time, which God had a right to, and which the Soul might have fared happily by, had it not been in a wicked Mans keeping. Intemperance, Luſt, Pride, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reling, ſtudying how to defraud, and to do Miſchief, robbeth away a great part of ſome Mens Lives; and worldly Intereſt is the common Thief, till improvident Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſee their Graves ready to open, to receive at laſt ſo many publick Nuſances, and ſo many Burdens upon the Earth. Theſe muſt needs be very melancholy Conſiderations to thoſe whoſe Eyes Death is a cloſing; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if their Conſciences are yet awake. And therefore People ſhould be wiſe in time, becauſe it is impoſſible for any of us to know, what the iſſues of a Death bed will be, or what our Condition will prove then. The <hi>Time paſt of our Life may ſuffice us to have wrought the Will of the Gentiles,</hi> ſaith <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. And thus every one of us ſhould conclude, the time paſt of our Life may ſuffice us to have followed the Works of the Fleſh, and the Vanities of the World. God knows, there are few, who have not loſt <hi>too much</hi> of this kind already; and, if
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150153:12"/>
inſtead of <hi>Recovering,</hi> Men go on ſtill to multiply their Loſſes, 'twill be a ſad Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they muſt come to at laſt, when they ſhall caſt up their Dammages, and their Acqueſts, and ſhall be made to conſider what a long Seaſon they have fool'd away, and gotten nothing by it in the end, but a wounded Conſcience, and a moſt terrible Proſpect.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150153:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150153:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150153:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How irreparable this Loſs will be in another Life.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THough this alone be a great Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, yet in compariſon of what follows, it is little to be valued. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever our Loſſes are now, as long as we have ſome time yet left us, we may make our ſelves ſome ſort of Reparation. But a Time is coming, which we ſhould always pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt, (the great cauſe of our trifling away ſo many precious hours, is, becauſe we do not think ſo much and ſo often as we ſhould of that Time) when, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the intimate Affection that is now between them, the Soul muſt be divorced from the Body, and live in a ſeparate State till the general Judgment-day. <hi>The Duſt ſhall return to the Earth as it was; and the Spirit ſhall return to God who gave it, Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7. It ſhall return unto God to receive its Sentence for the Works done in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and according as thoſe Works have been, whether good or evil, ſo will its State be aſſigned it, either of Happineſs or Miſery. And whatever that State be, it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150153:14"/>
will be utterly <hi>unchangeable.</hi> There can be no Reviving, till the Reſurrection; no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning upon the Earth any more; no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving over our Lives again, to rectifie any one Miſcarriage; no recalling a Minute, to drop a Tear, or to cry for Pardon. <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job) ſome bope of a Tree, if it be cut down, that it will ſprout again, and that the tender branch thereof will not ceaſe, though the root thereof wax old in the Earth, and the Stock thereof dye in the Ground; yet through the ſcent of Water it will bud, and bring forth boughs like a Plant. But a Man dieth, and waſteth away; yea, Man giveth up the Ghoſt, and where is he? As the Waters fail from the Sea, and the Flood decayeth and dryeth up, ſo Man lieth down, and riſeth not, till the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens be no more; They ſhall not awake, nor be raiſed out of their ſleep,</hi> Job 14. This Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration then is the <hi>ſecond Motive</hi> to quicken us all to <hi>Redeem our Time,</hi> becauſe the loſs of it at the end of this Life will be irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſeeing it is impoſſible for us to come out of our Graves again to order <hi>Time</hi> better then we are ſuppos'd to have done: We are deeply concerned to double our Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence about it now, before it is paſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> As yet it it not too late; but it will certainly be ſo, when once we are dead: Our Works will follow us into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; but it would be madneſs to think we may begin them there. which way ſoever our Souls go, we muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150153:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150153:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150153:16"/>
neceſſarily be Loſers, by loſing our <hi>Time</hi> here.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour tells us of a <hi>broad Way that leadeth to Deſtruction,</hi> Mat. 7. 13. And ſuch as go that way, are beyond all poſſibility of <hi>Redeeming their Time,</hi> or of being <hi>Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> themſelves, when once they arrive at the end of their ſad Journey. <hi>Hell</hi> indeed was prepared for the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and his <hi>Angels;</hi> and revealed to Men for their <hi>Terror;</hi> that the ſight of it might turn their Deſires towards <hi>Heaven,</hi> and frighten them into an eagerneſs of taking Sanctuary there, whither Promiſes alone would hardly allure ſordid and brutiſh Appetites. But if after ſuch proffers of infinite Happineſs, ſome will be ſo impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident and head-ſtrong, as to make that their Option, which is the Devils Curſe, they can blame none but themſelves for being at laſt without hope of Recovery. <hi>There the Worm dieth not, and the Fire is not quenched,</hi> as our Saviour aſſures us thrice together, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9. 44, 46, 48. Elſewhere it is called, <hi>Fire unquenchable,</hi> Mat. 3. 12. <hi>Fire Everlaſting,</hi> Mat. 25. 41. <hi>Fire Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> Jude 7. which is enough to prove the interminable duration of Hell-Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, againſt thoſe hardy Wretches, who would fain diſpute them away, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of endeavouring to prevent them. This is to ſtudy how to throw away two things which hang heavy upon them, their <hi>Time</hi> and their <hi>Faith</hi> too; though
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150153:16"/>
the loſs of either will be enough to make them miſerable. Perhaps the loſs of <hi>Time</hi> is the greateſt, becauſe it goes firſt; Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and other Wickedneſs being the Reſults of the loſs of <hi>Time,</hi> or that which is the conſequent of hours miſ-imployed. There are ſome Creatures which believe and tremble; and thoſe Sons of Perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on who bear them Company in weeping and wailing, and gnaſhing of Teeth, would give all the World, if they had it at command, <hi>for a few</hi> of thoſe days which many are ſo weary of, that they think of Methods, how to drive away their. <hi>Time:</hi> ſome by Idleneſs; ſome by Pride; ſome by Quarreling; ſome by Luſt; ſome by Intemperance; moſt by Vanity. Thoſe Portions of <hi>Time,</hi> how large ſoever they be, which Living-men ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, thoſe forlorn Souls which have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned themſelves to damnation, by not fore-caſting what now they feel, would think little enough to beſtow upon Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Prayers, and Acts of Charity; upon Expreſſions of Humility, and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial; upon the ſevereſt Mortifications; upon Sufferings of any ſorts (excepting their ſuffering the loſs of <hi>Time)</hi> they would be glad, though but of a few <hi>Minutes,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of our <hi>Years,</hi> to try if there might be any the leaſt room for <hi>Repentance.</hi> The Soul doth not forfeit its Eſſential Faculties, by being parted from the Fleſh. It retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtill Underſtanding, Memory, Will,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150153:17"/>
and Affections; ſuch I mean, as are ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to its State. Hope then can be none, when once it is come to the final Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its Fortunes. And yet, thus much may be gathered from the Parabolical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our Saviour gave of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the rich Man, <hi>Luk</hi> 16, That though the State of the Bleſſed, and the State of the Damned be immutably fixt on each hand by a <hi>Chaſm,</hi> or the irrevocable Decree of <hi>God,</hi> ſo that the damned have not any <hi>Hope</hi> for <hi>Themſelves;</hi> yet they have ſo much <hi>Charity,</hi> even in <hi>Hell,</hi> as to wiſh that their ſurviving Friends may not come into a Place, where they themſelves endure ſuch exquiſite Torments. And what would not ſuch Souls do on their own behalf, might they have ſome freſh time given them to beſtow upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets?</hi> To beſure they would part with all their <hi>Torments</hi> for one ſingle day; and yet year after year is now waſted, I do not ſay, in unprofitable, but in ungodly and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Courſes. What Nature doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, to ſupply its wants, <hi>Vice</hi> appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates a great ſhare of; though the <hi>World</hi> commonly goes away with the greateſt part; and that very ſmall Portion which is left for Offices of Religion, is ſpent often after ſuch a ſuperficial and careleſs man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that that too may be reckoned among Mens idle Expences, when a Meſſenger of Satan comes to deprive them of all, and to ſhut them under an utter impoſſibility
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150153:17"/>
of ever returning back to Redeem an Hour.</p>
               <p>Again, the Son of God tells us of a <hi>ſtrait Gate, and a narrow way, which leadeth unto Life,</hi> Mat. 7. 14. Now though in that bleſſed State every faithful Chriſtian will be crowned for all his Labors and Travels, and Sufferings under the Sun; yet in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf he will find ſome detriment by not Redeeming his <hi>Time</hi> here with that Diligence and Vigor which he ſhould have uſed. To ſpeak in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Words, though he ſpake them in reference to Trials and Perſecutions in this Life, 1 Cor. 3. 15. <hi>Such a Man ſhall ſuffer loſs, but he himſelf ſhall be ſaved.</hi> For, as there are Degrees of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in Hell, ſome beaten with fewer, and ſome with many Stripes, as they have ſquandred away their Time here leſs or more; ſo there are degrees of Felicities in Heaven, as Men have employed their Opportunities in this World, well, or <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> This inequality of Happineſs our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſufficiently intimates, <hi>by the many Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which he ſaith are in his Fathers Houſe,</hi> Jo. 14. 2. The Words in the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> are expreſs; <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament; and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12. 3. The Words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are to the like purpoſe; <hi>There is one Glory of the Sun, another Glory of the Moon, and another of the Stars; for one Star differeth from another Star in Glory: So alſo is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150153:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150153:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150153:19"/>
the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 41, 42. The Apoſtles words elſewhere are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond exception, <hi>He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly; and he which ſoweth boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, ſhall reap bountifully,</hi> 2 Cor. 9. 6. <hi>Every man ſhall receive his own reward according to his own Labour,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 8. From which places of Scripture it is clear, that tho all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at the hand of God be, not of Debt, but of pure Bounty, yet in the diſtribution of them the Divine Majeſty is pleaſed to make a difference between one Man and another, and to reward every one accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Quality and Meaſure of their Works. And hence it follows, that even ſuch as Love the Lord Jeſus in Sincerity, will Gain or Loſe in the other World, proportionably as they beſtow their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hours in this. They will have indeed the ſame moſt Bleſſed God to Contemplate, Love and Adore; the ſame ſorts and kinds of happineſs to enjoy; the ſame uninterrupted and Eternal Duration of it; and every Soul will be Repleniſhed with that Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the undeſerved goodneſs of God ſhall diſpenſe: But yet there will be various meaſures of Bliſs, tho it may be impoſſible for us now to expreſs the manner of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality, becauſe <hi>Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, neither hath it entred into the Heart of Man to conceive the things, which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that love him.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 9. 'Tis very probable, that the different degrees of Glory will be anſwerable to mens different Capacities; and as their Love to God now
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150153:19"/>
is leſs or more Perfect, according as thoſe heights of Affection are, which we attain to here; and according as the Powers of the Soul are improved and Exalted in this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant State, ſo will they ſtill be Raiſed and Perfected in Heaven; and conſequently the greater Meaſures of Happineſs we ſhall be capable of there. Hence it is, that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs are believed to be the neareſt unto Chriſt in Heaven, and to excel other Saints in Glory, becauſe by the more abundant Largeneſs of their Hearts in this Life, they were prepared to receive more abundant Degrees: and thoſe Converts who came later into the Vine-yard than others did, reach unto an equal pitch with them, if, like <hi>St. Paul,</hi> they make ſuch vaſt improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by their extraordinary Vigour and Zeal, as to overtake in their Labours ſuch as endured the Heat of the day. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we pretend to unfold the Manner and Reaſon of the thing, it is evident that in <hi>Fact</hi> there are ſeveral degrees of Happineſs, and that every one receiveth according to his Works.</p>
               <p>This ſhews how infinitely we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to redeem our time with all poſſible induſtry, not onely that we may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from the everlaſting Pains of a <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life;</hi> but <hi>moreover,</hi> that we may not miſs of thoſe great Hopes, or come ſhort of thoſe Expectations, we comfort our ſelves with now. Every man finds by experience, what an affliction it is to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150153:20"/>
eſpecially where the hopes were ſtrong, and the enjoyments deſired, of great conſequence. And though the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul will be ſo rectifyed in a <hi>ſtate of Perfection,</hi> that Heaven can be no place for <hi>dejecting</hi> and <hi>macerating</hi> griefs; yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive, but the ſenſe of former neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects muſt bring with it an Abatement of thoſe <hi>tranſcendent Joys,</hi> which otherwiſe would have been <hi>attainable.</hi> Nay, were there any room for a <hi>Sorrowful Repentance</hi> in thoſe bleſſed <hi>Regions</hi> above, the Saints there would <hi>repent</hi> of <hi>nothing</hi> more, then of the loſs of their time here, becauſe it is the <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Faults</hi> and <hi>Follies,</hi> which do ſet even <hi>Sincere Penitents</hi> in a Lower <hi>Claſſis,</hi> than thoſe who lived in an <hi>uninterrupted</hi> courſe of virtue and Piety.</p>
               <p>The ſumm is; that we ſhould manage our <hi>Expences</hi> of time with all pious and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Frugality;</hi> as being the moſt <hi>precious</hi> thing in this <hi>world,</hi> and as that which will <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate</hi> at laſt in an <hi>Immutable ſtate,</hi> where we ſhall <hi>certainly</hi> be ſavers or loſers to all <hi>eternity,</hi> as we Redeem, or not Redeem now. And would to God people would but ſet aſide ſome, though it were but a ſmall, part of every day to think what <hi>Eternity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports;</hi> and what it is to live without any end, without the leaſt <hi>Expectation,</hi> or Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of an end. Men would fain be <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal here;</hi> and act ſo unconcernedly, as if there were never to be an end of their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; of which this is one of the <hi>greatest,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150153:20"/>
the moſt <hi>Palpable:</hi> For dye we muſt in our reſpective turns; and as ſure as death, <hi>Judgement</hi> will follow; and as the ſentence is then, ſo will every ones lot hold on to <hi>Eternal</hi> ages, without ever coming to a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod.</hi> Conſidering therefore how <hi>unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> our ſtate will be, whether in woe or bliſs, and how our <hi>Everlaſting fortunes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the uſe we make of our time now, we are <hi>infinitely concern'd</hi> to Redeem what is loſt with a very quick hand, leſt our loſſes prove utterly and unexpectedly <hi>Irrecoverable;</hi> the time here is ſhort, at the beſt: The Pleaſures of ſin are but for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: The world paſſeth away <hi>gradually;</hi> people every day go away <hi>before</hi> it, and a few feet of Earth will in a little time ſerve to <hi>immure</hi> the moſt <hi>Inſatiable</hi> and <hi>Troubleſome</hi> man that is in it now. It would be a wiſe thing to look <hi>forward;</hi> and to <hi>conſider,</hi> in what a little ſpace there will be an end of a mans ſins and <hi>vanities</hi> here. In a few years <hi>Poſterity,</hi> to be ſure, will ſee a vaſt <hi>Alteration;</hi> there, the <hi>Haughty</hi> head laid Low; there, the <hi>Unconſcionable Oppreſſors</hi> cut down; there, the <hi>Luxurious</hi> thrown to nouriſh and fatten worms; there, the Luſtful brought to his <hi>Final Rottenneſs;</hi> there, the <hi>wanton</hi> eye cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; there the mouth of the <hi>Prophaneſt Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer</hi> is ſtopt; and there, a full end put to <hi>vicious courſes</hi> here; in all which time the ſouls of thoſe <hi>miſerable</hi> wretches are gone off, with an <hi>Eternity</hi> of Guilt upon them, to an <hi>Eternity</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> which we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150153:21"/>
ſhould lay cloſe to our hearts, could we ſee the <hi>Paſſages</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> of ſpirits, as we do <hi>Bodies,</hi> when they are carried upon mens <hi>ſhoulders</hi> to their graves. And yet <hi>conſidering,</hi> what we are told in our <hi>Creed,</hi> as to a future ſtate, and how <hi>Infallible Divine Revelation</hi> is, becauſe it cometh from God, who <hi>knoweth</hi> all things, and <hi>cannot poſſibly</hi> deceive, or be deceived; <hi>methinks nothing</hi> can quicken <hi>our endeavours</hi> to Redeem our time ſo much, as this ſole <hi>Reflection,</hi> what will become of us at the Laſt: but that men are <hi>generally Fools,</hi> in making ſuch <hi>unequal compariſons,</hi> as to ſet <hi>contingencies</hi> againſt <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties;</hi> and indeed to Prefer a few <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> before an <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150153:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How dangerous the loſs of time is, in reference to our preſent, outward fortunes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BUT beſides all this, we are to <hi>conſider,</hi> as the third motive, what may very Probably befal us even <hi>before</hi> we go to our Long homes, if we be not ſolicitous in time to Redeem our <hi>Loſt hours.</hi> It is a Loſs, that may be very <hi>dangerous</hi> in reference to our preſent <hi>outward fortunes.</hi> For the <hi>illuſtration</hi> of this matter we are to note, that God <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> upon his time, when he will make <hi>Careleſs</hi> and <hi>Incorrigible</hi> people <hi>Examples</hi> of his <hi>Justice</hi> in this <hi>world.</hi> Though it be one of thoſe ſecret things which belong unto the <hi>Lord</hi> our God, yet the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> gives us <hi>warrant</hi> to believe, that ſuch a fix't time there is, when he viſits <hi>Negligent</hi> peoples of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences with a Rod, and their ſins with <hi>Scourges;</hi> eſpecially this ſin, the miſ-ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe days and hours, which he is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to allot them for works of Piety and <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> Gods purpoſe <hi>concerning</hi> the old world was, that their days ſhould be an <hi>hundred and twenty years, Gen.</hi> 6. 3. which is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150153:22"/>
not to be <hi>underſtood</hi> ſo, as if he intended to contract peoples lives by ſhortning the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al term of <hi>Nature,</hi> which in thoſe ages was very long: but that he would in ſix ſcore years put an end to the world that then was, and deſtroy all but eight perſons by a floud, unleſs they did Repent of thoſe great wickedneſſes, by Reaſon whereof <hi>it grieved God at the heart, that he had made man on the earth, Gen.</hi> 6. 6. It is obſervable, that our Bleſſed Saviour ſpeaking of a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judgment, that after his aſcention would come upon the unbelieving Jews; and directing his diſciples to ſtrict vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, for fear they too ſhould be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd and deſtroyed with the reſt, makes uſe of this very inſtance as a powerful argument to make them watchful; <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 37, 38, 39. <q>As the days of <hi>Noah</hi> were, ſo ſhall alſo the coming of the Son of Man be: for as in the days that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud they were eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, marrying and giving in marriage, untill the days that <hi>Noah</hi> entred into the Ark; and knew (or; Conſidered) not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the floud came and took them all away, ſo ſhall alſo the <hi>coming</hi> of the Son of man be.</q> Which ſhews, that the great cauſe of the general deluge was, the general ſin of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſquandring away their <hi>pretious</hi> time upon Pleaſures, Riots and Debauchery, when God hath ſet them their Bounds, beyond which he reſolves they ſhould not live any longer. The <hi>Time</hi> God pitched
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150153:22"/>
upon for the Deſtruction of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> was the <hi>Fourth Generation</hi> from the Days of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15. 16. That he ſent to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh</hi> was <hi>forty Days, Jonab</hi> 3. 4. And by the Hiſtory it appears, that the ſpace fixed for the Deſtruction of the <hi>Jews</hi> after the Lord Jeſus his departure, was <hi>forty years;</hi> the time that had been ſpent in <hi>bringing their Anceſtors into the Poſſeſſion of the Promiſed Land.</hi> The <hi>intermediate</hi> ſpace before their Overthrow, is called <hi>Jeruſalems Day, Luke</hi> 19. 42. <hi>O that thou</hi> (Jeruſalem) <hi>hadst known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy Peace</hi>! Gods day was to be the next; a day of Horror and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that preſently came upon <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as ſoon as ſhe had Trifled and ſinned away her <hi>Own.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe few inſtances it appears, that God determines upon a certain <hi>Time,</hi> when he will Puniſh People Remarkably, if they do not Prevent his Judgments by Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Time, while it is <hi>yet</hi> called, <hi>To day.</hi> Whence it followeth, that could men be ſo Fooliſh as to disbelieve a Future State, their preſent welfare would require them to <hi>Redeem their Time;</hi> becauſe the more they Procraſtinate, and the longer they defer that neceſſary Work, ſo many degrees the day of Temporal Vengeance appraocheth; and the nearer that draweth <hi>towards them,</hi> and the more ſteps <hi>they</hi> take to <hi>meet it,</hi> the more <hi>imminent</hi> ſtill is the danger of <hi>dropping</hi> into unexpected Ruin. This was St. <hi>Pauls</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150153:23"/>
own Argument for the <hi>Redeeming of Time,</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>The days are Evil,</hi> Eph. 5. 16. By Evil days the Scripture ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meaneth <hi>Old Age,</hi> and days of <hi>Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity:</hi> And ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the days of thy Youth, while the evil days come not.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed 'tis a proper Admonition for People in that Caſe, to make a nimble uſe of their <hi>Time,</hi> to accelerate their Courſe, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day to make the quicker and quicker diſpatches; like Bodies, whoſe motion is the ſwifter and ſtronger, the nearer they come to their place of Reſt. But by <hi>Evil days</hi> the Apoſtle means, times of <hi>Peril</hi> and <hi>Danger;</hi> and when any Juncture is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it is high time for People to be on the Redeeming hand; becauſe God hath ſet <hi>His Day,</hi> if they do not beſtow <hi>theirs</hi> as he would have them.</p>
               <p>When they Act with that Zeal, Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and Circumſpection, which becomes thoſe who are certain otherwiſe to be quite undone, then the Rod is laid up, and the Viſitation is put off to another day; and ſo on ſtill; the farther and farther it is defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the more Induſtriouſly they go on, and perſevere in <hi>Well-doing.</hi> For God's Menaces are conditional; he doth always reſerve to himſelf a power of Revocation, and ſtill exerts it by delivering Men from danger, as they do their part in anſwering the great Ends of the Sentence. When <hi>they</hi> Redeem their <hi>Time,</hi> God Redeems
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150153:23"/>
                  <hi>Them</hi> and their <hi>Fortunes</hi> from Deſtruction, and then he is ſaid to <hi>Repent</hi> of the Evil: 'Tis ſpoken after the manner of <hi>Men,</hi> in condeſcention to our Capacities; when upon our due Reformation he <hi>Removes</hi> a Judgment, which he intended otherwiſe to bring upon us. At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Kingdom, to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it; <hi>If that Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom I have pronounced, turn from their Evil, I will repent of the Evil, that I thought to do unto them,</hi> Jer. 18 7, 8. <hi>Upon this Account,</hi> the Apoſtles Argument, taken from the Conſideration of dangerous Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is of great force; becauſe Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is the firſt Principle of Nature, and that which too often works even <hi>againſt Principles of Religion;</hi> but when Religion comes to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> it, by ſhewing People the Vengeance of God over their Heads, it ſerves to ſet all hands at work upon the <hi>Reedeeming of Time,</hi> to prevent a Storm, wherein otherwiſe they are likely to periſh. Many that are contented to run the hazards of another Life, are very unwilling to loſe the Comforts of this, becauſe they love the Preſent, and their Senſes are too ſtrong for <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the <hi>Subſtance of things not ſeen, but hoped for,</hi> Heb. 11. 1. Therefore when <hi>preſent</hi> dangers are throughly apprehended, Endeavors to avoid them will naturally follow. In ſuch a caſe, People will no more loſe <hi>Time,</hi> then they will lye in their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150153:24"/>
Beds, if they know the Houſe is ready to be burnt. Now, as certain as Natural Cauſes work, ſo certain it is, that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will overtake thoſe who care not how vainly and wickedly they ſpend their days. It is that which ſeals Men up to Deſtruction, as it did the <hi>Sodomites:</hi> amongſt whoſe Iniquities, abundance of <hi>Idleneſs</hi> is reckoned as one, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17 49. that which drew on a great many Wickedneſſes more, and at laſt turned the whole City into a great Globe of Fire. Therefore when the Hand of God in the leaſt appears, it is an awakening Argument for us all to riſe from our Security, and to Redeem the Time, while we have as yet any Opportunities left us; For the longer we defer this Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, the harder God will be to be intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; till in the end he will become utterly inexorable. This ſeems to be clear from the Parallel, which the Apoſtle draweth from the Caſe of <hi>Eſau,</hi> Heb. 12. 17. <hi>For a Morſel of Meat he ſold his Birth right, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards loſt his Fathers Bleſſing by Hunting. Jacob</hi> made ſuch an uſe of his Brothers Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and of his own <hi>Time,</hi> that he gat the Bleſſing from him. <hi>Eſau</hi> would have recovered it, but was rejected, becauſe he came too late. <hi>He found</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>no Place of Repentance, though he ſought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with Tears;</hi> meaning that he could not perſwade his <hi>Father to Repent of what he had done,</hi> ſo as to alter his Mind, and to recal the thing that had gone out of his Lips.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150153:24"/>
This inſtance the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> makes uſe of as a Reaſon, why we ſhould take heed <hi>leſt we fail of the grace of God,</hi> or forfeit our title to his merciful <hi>Protection;</hi> which yet would be of no force, nor indeed to the purpoſe, if it were not poſſible for us to fare as ill as <hi>Eſau</hi> did. But St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words ſhew, that though God be a God of Patience and long ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet there is a time when he will ſtay no longer for thoſe who turn his Grace into <hi>wantonneſs;</hi> when he will be deaf to their cries; and will not be prevailed with to Repent of the evil that he hath pronounced againſt them. I now ſpeak of ſuch evils as God brings upon men in <hi>this</hi> life; where Puniſhments are Examplary; inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on people for good; for the <hi>Correction</hi> of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provident</hi> people themſelves, and for the <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> of all. The pains of another world are purely <hi>Vindictive;</hi> and ſuch as are both Remedileſs and Endleſs; and therefore God leaves room for mercy to the very Laſt hour of life, when Repentance on our part is <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and ſincere: witneſs the acceptance that penitent theif upon the Croſs found; whoſe caſe, though it was Particular, and not to be drawn into example ſo as to encourage any wretches to throw away their time upon preſumption of mercy at the Laſt; yet it argues plainly, that <hi>at what hour ſoever a Sinner turneth from his evil way he ſhall ſave his Soul alive.</hi> But this doth not always ſave people from Puniſhments here; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch People, as have long <hi>Abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:150153:25"/>
the Patience and Goodneſs of God. To this purpoſe, we may obſerve what was ſaid of <hi>Jeruſalem, Luk.</hi> 19. 42. that the things which belonged unto her peace were hidden from her eyes; and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it is given <hi>v.</hi> 44 <hi>becauſe ſhe knew not the time of her viſitation;</hi> that is, ſhe did not conſider her own great intereſt in time; ſhe would not lay the things belonging to her peace to Heart, notwithſtanding ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calls, firſt from the Prophets that had been ſent to her, and at Laſt from the mouth of the Son of God himſelf, the Lord of life and Glory. The Reſult of this is, that people may quite Sin away their day of Peace; and becauſe the more time they loſe, the greater their <hi>dangers</hi> are, they ſhould be very diligent while they have fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities; while there is a <hi>Seaſon, an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time, a day of ſalvation. Seek ye the Lord while he may be found,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 6. <hi>Call upon him while he is near;</hi> intimateing clearly, that there is a critical Juncture, when he will not be found, but keep off at a great diſtance, though he be fought after. And to this purpoſe are theſe following Texts of Scripture, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 24. &amp;c. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand, and no man regarded;</hi> but <hi>ye have ſet at nought all my counſel, and would none of my Reproof; I alſo will Laugh at your Calamity, I will mock when your fear cometh; when your fear cometh as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and your Diſtruction cometh as a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150153:25"/>
whirlwind; when diſtreſs and anguiſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon you: Then ſhall they call upon me, but will not anſwer, they ſhall ſeek me early, but ſhall not find me.</hi> Iſa. 65. 12. <hi>Therefore will I number you to the ſword, and ye ſhall all bow down to the ſlaughter, becauſe when I called, ye did not anſwer; when I ſpake, ye did not hear, but did evil before mine eyes, and did chuſe that wherein I delighted not.</hi> And Iſa. 7. 15, 16. <hi>I will caſt you out of my ſight, as I have caſt out all your brethren, even the whole ſeed of</hi> Ephraim; <hi>therefore pray thou not for this people, neither lift up cry nor prayer for them, neither make interceſſion to me; for I will not hear thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From theſe ſeveral <hi>places it appears,</hi> that Gods decrees, which in the beginning were Conditional, at length come to be Peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; and that ſentence to be Final and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable, which was originally deſigned not for mens <hi>Destruction,</hi> but for their amendment: and becauſe this proceeds from the miſ-ſpending thoſe hours, which God numbreth out unto us all, that we may do the world and our own Souls good, it nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly concerns us to Redeem our time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be too Late. <hi>To day if you will hear his voice; harden not your hearts,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt; as if the deferring of it to another day were a ready courſe to harden our own ſpirits and to make God ſilent to all our cryes in the day of vengeance. This is <hi>your hour, and the power of darkneſs,</hi> as Chriſt told thoſe malicious wretches, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 53. But Gods power will take its turn, when his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150153:26"/>
own time cometh: and becauſe of that day and hour knoweth no man, but it is wont to ſteal upon Improvident people when they look not for it, nor are aware of it, we ſhould be every minute, watchful and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by Improving the time <hi>Preſent</hi> to the beſt advantage. Who can tell <hi>what a day will bring forth?</hi> Or what ſhall be <hi>on the morrow?</hi> and conſidering, how uncertain this world is, and how <hi>Croſs</hi> events uſually prove, whatever we <hi>Project or hope for,</hi> we ſhould not let any bleſſed <hi>opportunities</hi> ſlip away, nor <hi>be Loytering about,</hi> while the main buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>ſtays</hi> for us, left ſudden <hi>deſtruction</hi> come upon us, <hi>as travail upon a woman with child, while we ſay, Peace and ſafety,</hi> like thoſe <hi>fooliſh people</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5, 3.</p>
               <p>And <hi>would God</hi> we of this <hi>Kingdom would ſeriouſly</hi> lay this thing to heart, while the great <hi>Goodneſs of God</hi> towards us doth yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure! Though we are as apt, as any <hi>Nation,</hi> to flatter our ſelves with <hi>promiſes</hi> of Peace and ſafety; eſpecially <hi>conſidering how</hi> many years experience we have had of <hi>Gods merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> and indeed <hi>miraculous</hi> Providence over us; yet we cannot but diſcern what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers threaten the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> at this time; and it is to be wiſn't, that that time which ſome trifle away in murmurings and <hi>Complaints,</hi> we would all of us be perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to employ upon act; of unfeigned <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> that God may be intreated for us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his arm is ſtretched out to cut us off in the midſt of <hi>our</hi> ſecurity. As <hi>we</hi> have loſt <hi>time,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150153:26"/>
ſo Gods Judgements have gained <hi>ground;</hi> nor is there any other way left us <hi>now,</hi> but to recover what we can of our Loſſes by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Quick uſe of the <hi>Remainder, according</hi> to the <hi>Laws of Religion,</hi> and true Chriſtian Prudence. Should ſuch <hi>deſolation</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs be <hi>brought upon</hi> us, which ſome other <hi>Nations groan</hi> under, it will be too late to ſay, we did not imagine that things would have come to this paſs. We have, God knows, little reaſon to think, we are better than other people. If we were not <hi>worſe, our hopes</hi> of ſafety might be the better grounded. But by how much <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm</hi> and <hi>Irreligion go beyond ſuperſtition,</hi> by ſo much are <hi>our provocations</hi> greater, and our ſins the more crying and importunate, to bring down that vengeance, which we ſee hovering over our heads. Therefore, the wiſeſt, and the moſt effectual courſe, we can take to prevent our Ruine is, to lay hold on thoſe fair <hi>opportunities</hi> we have, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are out of our reach, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the time while God is yet pleaſed to give us Leave.</p>
               <p>The Promiſes being duly and throughly conſider'd, will. I hope, be able enough to carry your thoughts on to the laſt great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; <hi>viz.</hi> How we may order the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo as to Redeem our time to very <hi>good</hi> purpoſe?</p>
               <p>In order hereunto theſe five things are neceſſary:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150153:27"/>
Firſt, to Kindle and preſerve in our hearts a true Chriſtian Zeal.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to conſider what ſins we have acted, and to make all poſſible amends for them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to do all the good we can:</p>
               <p>Fourthly, to let no day ſlip away whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without <hi>promoting</hi> our eternal intereſt in ſome degree and meaſure.</p>
               <p>And Fifthly, to ſpend as much as may be of the Remainder of our time upon <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> eſpecially upon the <hi>Solemnities</hi> of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Devotion</hi> in the <hi>houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150153:27"/>
               <head>CHAP V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The way to Redeem our time is, firſt, to Kindle and preſerve in our hearts a true Chriſtian Zeal.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>1. THE Firſt courſe to be taken is, to Kindle and Preſerve in our hearts a <hi>True Chriſtian Zeal.</hi> By a true Chriſtian Zeal I underſtand, a <hi>Warm</hi> and <hi>well Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Reſolution to act according to Chriſt's Laws. For there are two ſorts of Zeal which are <hi>Faulty.</hi> One, is that which is not according <hi>to Knowledge,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 2. a blind Paſſion, or Impetus that hurries all before it upon <hi>Preſumptions</hi> and miſtakes; and without a deliberate Calm <hi>Examination</hi> of the true merits of the Cauſe. Such a Zeal was his <hi>Own,</hi> while he yet breathed out threatnings and ſlaughter againſt the diſciples of the Lord. <hi>He verily thought, that he was bound to do many things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the name of Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 9. This was his <hi>miſtaken</hi> Zeal; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he obtained mercy afterwards, becauſe, what he had done, he did <hi>Ignorantly in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, Tim.</hi> 1. 3. There is another ſort of Zeal which is not according <hi>to Sobriety;</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150153:28"/>
an Inordinate heat of mind, and that too miſ-applyed, upon objects that are not ſo proper; though the mans Judgment be right and found: when Zeal is employed about minute matters in <hi>compariſon;</hi> about the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials, and petite Appendages, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than about the eſſentials of <hi>Religion:</hi> Such a Zeal was theirs, who were ſtrict and nice about <hi>Mint, Anis,</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> but omitted the weightier matters of the Law, Righteouſneſs, mercy, and Faith; theſe things ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Math.</hi> 23. 23. Our Zeal ſhould be attended with <hi>Light,</hi> as well as <hi>Warmth;</hi> with Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, and due Application, as well as fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency; and then 'tis a well governed Zeal; a <hi>Diſpoſition</hi> made up of a right Principle, and of due temper and Prudence.</p>
               <p>Now ſuch a ſober earneſtneſs of mind is abſolutely neceſſary in order to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming of our time, becauſe it is the ſource and ſpring of action; the natural principle of all vigorous performances; without which we ſhall be ſo far from <hi>doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> our diligence, that we ſhall expreſs <hi>none at all;</hi> but indulge our ſelves with the ſluggard, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>A Requiem</hi> is all he minds; he makes his life literally a <hi>Dream;</hi> yet a <hi>little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little more fold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the hands to ſleep.</hi> A bed is an impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place to Redeem time; which ſlides away there <hi>inſenſibly:</hi> and a ſpirit of ſlumber, and an active mind, are as great contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150153:28"/>
as Reſt and work are. There muſt be at leaſt, ſuch a principle of Zeal in this caſe, as there is of Induſtry in other caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; a principle that ſtirs people up to their Buſineſs and Pleaſures in their <hi>common</hi> courſe of life. They that love the <hi>World,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grudge no time they lay out upon it; but riſe up early, ſit up late, and eat the bread of ſorrows, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 2. The reaſon is; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have an inordinate and ſorded Zeal for <hi>Mammon;</hi> it is that inward Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that makes them Reſtleſs, and takes away from them the general comforts of mankind; though for the ſake of the world they count that ſtealth no manner of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery. The <hi>Voluptuous</hi> care not how many hours they throw away upon the Pleaſures of ſin. They wait for the Twilight, <hi>Pro.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>They tarry long at the wine, Prov.</hi> 23. 30. They riſe up early in the morning, that they may follow ſtrong drink, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue until night, till it inflames them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 11. In ſhort; whatever peoples hearts are ſet upon, they will be ſure to follow with <hi>Induſtry</hi> and <hi>eagerneſs:</hi> and the true Reaſon, why they are ſo ſparing of their time in the buſineſs of Religion, is becauſe they want ſuch a <hi>Principle</hi> of vigour as makes them profuſe and Prodigal in other caſes. Hence it is, that the Bed or the Belly rob the Cloſet, becauſe their minds are not there, that ſports and paſtime go away with thoſe hours, which meditation ſhould take up; and that ſuch portions of the day are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150153:29"/>
upon vanity and vice, which ſhould be expended upon <hi>Prayer.</hi> Hence it is too, that the Houſe of God is ſo neglected; that the <hi>Altar</hi> is paſt by, when all things are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy but peoples Hearts; and that they think it long till the Sabbath be over, as thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> did, <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 5. The Reaſon of all this is, becauſe they are Lovers of other things, more then of God, or Religion, or their own eternal Happineſs; there is not that true Chriſtian Zeal, which would render all theſe things a <hi>Delight,</hi> at leaſt would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent them as <hi>Duties,</hi> inſtead of counting them a <hi>Burden.</hi> As long as men ſlight <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> or are cold and Indifferent about it, we cannot expect they ſhould Redeem their time to any Good purpoſe. To quicken and ſtir up all our minds for that weighty matter, we ſhould warm our hearts with a brisk and enlivening ſenſe of our duty, and of the Conſequents which depend upon it; we ſhould call to mind the vaſt advantages which ſhall be the reward of a <hi>good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and the Preſent pleaſures which inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably attend a godly, righteous, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber life. We ſhould often reflect upon the vain, Empty, Periſhing <hi>condition</hi> of all <hi>Word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> matters; that after all our Arts and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> for them, we muſt leave them all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and can carry nothing away, but our <hi>Conſciences</hi> and works; we ſhould daily <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</hi> that we muſt all dye, and after Death go to Judgement; and think with our ſelves, what terrible times thoſe will be; what a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150153:29"/>
                  <hi>Precious</hi> thing an Immortal Soul is; how unchangeable its ſtate will be hereafter, whether it be in miſery or Bliſs; and what a <hi>Fooliſh</hi> thing 'twill be to Loſe it though it were for the Gaining of ten thouſand worlds now. We ſhould conſider with all, what cares are neceſſary for the ſaving of a Soul; How many things we are to do, and what Little time we have to do them all in; How our days paſs away like a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; how very <hi>uncertain</hi> the <hi>ſhortneſs</hi> of them is; how many accidents there are to cut us off before Nature hath ſpun out her work to the Full; of what <hi>dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> Delays are; what a diſmal thing it will be to be ſurpriz'd on a ſudden; and how Contingent the iſſues of Repentance may be, though any ill man be permitted to lye long upon his ſick bed, with Friends and Prayers about him.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like <hi>Religious</hi> meditations, if rightly entertain'd, will be apt, to inſpire us with warm <hi>Reſolutions,</hi> to Redeem our time, while it is yet in our hand; to make us <hi>Cautious</hi> of Loſing a day more; and to invigorate our ſouls with ſuch an hearty <hi>principle</hi> as will render us, not onely <hi>Diligent,</hi> but very <hi>Zealous</hi> and <hi>Eager</hi> in a Chriſtian courſe, which puts me in mind of the <hi>vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Reſolutions</hi> of that great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> St. <hi>Paul;</hi> whoſe indefatigable Induſtry and Zeal to Redeem the time he had Loſt, is a Noble pattern for ours, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14. <hi>I follow after,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>forgetting thoſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150153:30"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:150153:30"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150153:31"/>
things which are behind, and reaching forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe things which are before; I preſs on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the mark, for the Prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> He there compared himſelf to one that was running a Race, to obtain a Garland at the <hi>Mark,</hi> or <hi>Goal,</hi> or <hi>Race-end.</hi> Thoſe which are engaged in ſuch an <hi>Athletick Courſe,</hi> are not wont to ſtop and loiter away their Minutes, or to ſtand looking behind them to ſee what lengths and diſtances they have ran, and how far they have out-ſtript the Cumba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants that are ſhort of them; but ſtrive and ſtretch forward, each ſtraining every Sinew to overtake and out-run the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, that he may receive the Prize firſt. And thus did St. <hi>Paul</hi> proceed with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Zeal, and Earneſtneſs in that Spiritual Courſe, wherein he was a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batant (though a late one) <hi>for a Crown that withereth not, nor fadeth away.</hi> He was on the purſuit; he made as much ſpeed as was poſſible; ſtrove hard, and went on vigorouſly from one labor and difficulty to another; he fetch'd up and recover'd the Time he had miſ-ſpent, by Toiling and Working, and Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling more abundantly than the reſt; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient Day and Night, till he had out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, and out-done thoſe that had been called before him, and ſtill preſſing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and ſtretching on, for the Prize he had in his Eye, that Eternal weight
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150153:31"/>
of Glory, which was laid up for him in the Heavens.</p>
               <p>By this inſtance we ſee, what a warm and well govern'd Zeal is; how power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its Influence; what Life and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour it creates, and what wonderful Works it can do in a little Time, when a Man is reſolved to Redeem it indeed. And that we may follow St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Example, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſet up (as he did) a ſerious and obſtinate Reſolution, to do God Service from our <hi>Hearts,</hi> and our ſelves and others all the good we can, while we have fair Opportunities before us. Such a Chriſtian Zeal will make Us too active and nimble in <hi>running the Race that is ſet before us;</hi> 'twill carry us with Patience and Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy through All; ſo that no Pains will be begrudged; no thoughts of Difficulty will put us to a ſtand; no apprehenſions of Danger will make us faint; no ſenſe of Diſcouragements will caſt us down; 'twill help us to go on ſtill from Vertue to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, fearful of nothing, but of loſing <hi>Time;</hi> till at laſt we come to that great pitch St. <hi>Paul</hi> attained to, <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith; henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, ſhall give me at that day; and not to me only, but to all them alſo, that love his appearing,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 7, 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150153:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſecond way is, to conſider what Sins we have acted, and to make all poſſible amends for them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> THis zealous Diſpoſition being form'd in our Minds, the next way to Redeem our time is, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what <hi>Sins we have acted, and to make all poſſible amends for them.</hi> The time that is flung away upon vice is not meerly <hi>loſt, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed wickedly;</hi> and in this caſe there is as much difference between loſing and waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as there is between Idleneſs and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; or, between doing nothing at all, and doing that which is Evil. Now here the way of Redeeming ones time is, as far as 'tis poſſible, to undoe that which hath been done; and to perform ſuch acts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, as are declarative of our hearty wiſhes, that the things had never been done at all. For, to <hi>continue</hi> in a wicked <hi>Courſe,</hi> or, not to make ſome <hi>Reparation</hi> for a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Act</hi> is a ſpending of time as Ill, as at the firſt; becauſe it carries with it a tacit <hi>Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation</hi> of mind, which is <hi>Tantamount</hi> to the <hi>Committing</hi> it again over and over. Nay, Sins continued in, or un-repented, are more
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150153:32"/>
pernicious in their <hi>Conſequence,</hi> than they were in the original; becauſe they harden the heart, and by degrees draw ſuch a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty temper upon the <hi>Conſcience</hi> as makes it inſenſate; ſo that the loſing of time <hi>on,</hi> is the ready means of making one uncapable at laſt of Redeeming it at all. This ſhews, that by perſiſting in that which is evil, inſtead of <hi>recovering the hours</hi> that <hi>were wickedly</hi> ſpent, men miſemploy them <hi>ſtill,</hi> and make the matter daily <hi>worſe</hi> and <hi>worſe.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when an ill thing is acted, they <hi>ſhould endeavour</hi> to obliterate it by a very ſpeedy repentance; and the <hi>ſooner</hi> they come to it, the more time and <hi>Innocence</hi> they ſave, and the quicklier they make all Right again. An inſtance to this purpoſe we read of in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Cenſures on thoſe who had <hi>committed</hi> ſome <hi>Scandalous Enormities,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7, 9, 11. <hi>Ye were made Sorry, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, after a godly manner;—And that your Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, what carefulneſs it wrought in you? Yea, what clearing of your ſelves? Yea, what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation? Yea, what Fear? Yea, what ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement Deſire? Yea, what Zeal? Yea, what Revenge.</hi> That is, their ſpeedy Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance had ſuch great effects upon them, that they were very <hi>Solicitous</hi> to expiate their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; they purged themſelves preſently of the crimes committed; they expreſt their Diſpleaſure and vexation for the <hi>commſſion</hi> of them; they were afraid of offending God any more; they ſhewed all readineſs to give
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150153:33"/>
the Church Satisfaction for what had been done among them; they declared their firm <hi>Reſolutions</hi> of <hi>Reforming</hi> for the time to come; and they uſed all poſſible ſeverities, to inflict Puniſhment upon themſelves, for the wrongs they had done their own ſouls, and for the Reproach they had brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their moſt holy <hi>Profeſſion.</hi> This is a Right way for people to Redeem their time; becauſe it is in effect, to deſtroy and ſpoil the works of their hands; to make the days periſh wherein they did amiſs; and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin their lives a new, as if thoſe days had never been.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>ſtrictly</hi> ſpeaking, we cannot ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Null our works, ſo as to make thoſe things never to have been, which are actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Paſt; yet <hi>Moraly,</hi> and by <hi>Interpretation</hi> we may Annihilate our actions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke what is gone, if our Repentance be Hearty and opperative like that which thoſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> expreſt.</p>
               <p>Now here men ſhould examine the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of their crimes paſt, that they may redeem their time by ſuch <hi>Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> for them, and ſuch holy revenges up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves as are ſuitable.</p>
               <p>Some ſins are <hi>Injurious</hi> to the Souls of the <hi>Actors</hi> only; ſuch as a man committeth alone, and by himſelf, without any witneſs of them, but his own Conſcience and God. In this caſe the right courſe is, to betake ones ſelf to Private, but ſincere humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to deprecate God's wrath; to chaſten
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150153:33"/>
the Soul by Faſting and ſevere <hi>mortifications;</hi> to beſtow more time than uſual upon <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and Prayer; to break off ones ſins by Righteouſneſs, and ones iniquities by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy to the Poor; and above all, to leave the ſin, or ſins, entirely off, and by the continual exerciſe of contrary vertues to bring the mind to a regular frame and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. This is to undoe an Evil action, to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel all that Guilt which is <hi>Private, Perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> and <hi>Single,</hi> to Recover what is paſt and gone, by ſuch a moral Revocation as God will accept of, and for Chriſt's ſake Impute to the ſincere Penitent as Amends for his former miſcarriages.</p>
               <p>There are other ſins which are of a more <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Peſtilential</hi> nature: Sins, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the inward Guilt they bring upon the actors Conſcience, carry along with them outward infection, miſchief and ſcandal, as Defamation, Lying, Adultery, evil Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, Injuſtice of all ſorts, and whatever wickedneſs elſe is exemplary and hurtful to other men. Theſe crimes are much the worſe, becauſe it is a very difficult (and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times impoſſible) matter to make full amends and ſatisfaction for them, (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to Redeem the time they have loſt; becauſe the ſin may ſpread ſo far, and may laſt ſo long in its miſchievous effects, as to be out of ones Reach and Power to Recal it, ſo as to Null it utterly. In this caſe therefore the only means a man hath left him to Redeem his time is, to do what
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150153:34"/>
he is <hi>Able towards</hi> the Revocation of his wickedneſs; and that muſt be, not only to ceaſe from doing it any more, but <hi>moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> to make all poſſible Reparation for what hath been done already; were it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Private, ſingle</hi> guilt, the Conſcience might be diſcharged of it by thoſe ways I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned juſt now; but conſidering that it is <hi>complicated</hi> and <hi>aggravated</hi> by the Addition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al guilt of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Scandal,</hi> much more is required to wipe it off. All poſſible means muſt be uſed to cure the miſchievous <hi>effects</hi> of ſuch criminal actions; the <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> of them muſt be ſtopt, and Amends made for the hurt done before the revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; becauſe without this the whole ſin cannot be undone, but is rather avowed and Continued in, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and in effect Repeated every day; upon which account the wretch is ſo far from Redeeming his time, that he Trifles it away, and ſins it on <hi>still;</hi> every hour of his life is Loſt; his Prayers, all Loſt; his very Repentance, whatever it be, is loſt too, becauſe it is ſo ſhort and Imperfect; and ſhould ſuch a man live to a Decrepite old age, he would be as far from Gods Pardon, as when the ſin was firſt acted; and indeed much farther, by reaſon of the Long, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated</hi> aggravation of his Guilt, by Perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill in the wickedneſs, and by permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the malignity of it to run on. For the Illuſtration of this matter it is neceſſary to put ſome particular caſes; and they ſhall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150153:34"/>
be theſe Four. Firſt, if a man once cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth his neighbours wife, or virgin, or whatever the condition of the fooliſh crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be, with whom the villany is acted; it is not enough to act it no more; there is an Injury done, and that which may be Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and eternal; whether it will not prove ſo, is more than the Adulterer knows: he has done his part to damn her Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and her Soul too; and therefore it is not ſufficient to forbear for the future, no more than it is for a Murtherer to proceed no further, when he has already given a mortal ſtabb; in this caſe all poſſible endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſhould be uſed for the <hi>Saving</hi> of life; as in the other, all poſſible means muſt be applyed for the ſaving of a <hi>Soul.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhall periſh or no, it is at Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in whoſe hand it is: But whatever the ſucceſs may be, all ways of Reparation muſt be <hi>Try'd;</hi> otherwiſe the Sin is ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betted and Perſiſted in, till the Adulterers own Soul be paſt Redemption, as well as his <hi>Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again; <hi>a Good Name is better than precious ointment,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccl.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>And if an enemy take it away by Libels or Lyes, nay, though it be uncharitable Truths, the wrong is manifeſt;</hi> nor will it ſuffice (though that be more than ſome will do) to forbear at length to throw about the Poiſon of an <hi>Aſp:</hi> the <hi>Viper</hi> has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done his venemous work and whether the Defamation doth ſtick long or no, the Guilt of it ſticks upon the ſlanderers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150153:35"/>
there it reſteth till <hi>Satisfaction</hi> be made for the calumny, and an effectual courſe be taken to ſet the good mans Name right again, and to Reſtore it to its former Savour; for as long as the ſtench continues, the Sin <hi>operates;</hi> the wretch hath ſtill the Guilt, though he thinks it to be the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of the Serpent: nor is it poſſible for him to wipe it off, but by his Recovering that which he cauſed to be Loſt; by applying ſome ſuch Antidote to expel the poiſon, as Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts ſay the very worſt of Serpents yeild. Till a Recantation gives a check, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny goes on, and conſequently his Guilt; and inſtead of Redeeming his time, he loſeth more. Thirdly; in the caſe of Theft, or oppreſſion (which is defrauding and Theeving by dint of <hi>Power)</hi> there is to be conſider'd, beſides the ſinfulneſs of the Act, the Injury that attends it. Now tho it be very Right, what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſays, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 28. <hi>Let him that ſtole, ſteal no more;</hi> yet this is no Redeeming of time without ſome Compenſation; becauſe the man is a wrongful Poſſeſſor of anothers Propriety, nor can Poſſeſſion ever give him a Title to that which is not founded upon Juſtice. There muſt be therefore <hi>Reſtitution</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ones <hi>Power; Reſtitution</hi> in kind, or Equivalence; otherwiſe, the ſin Remaines, though committed but once, becauſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury continues; and ſo, both the ſin and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury will continue on, till both be expiated
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150153:35"/>
and aboliſh't by ſatisfaction. 4. Laſtly; if by evil <hi>Inſtructions,</hi> or worſe example one man leads another into Error, or Impiety, the true way for him to Redeem his time after all is, to Cure the miſchief by an hearty <hi>retractation</hi> errors many times ſpread like a Gangrene, inſenſibly, ſpeedily, and mortally: and ſuch as have been guilty of caſting the venome, muſt not (though they Repent) think their Conſciences ſufficiently diſcharged by forbearing for the future: here Double diligence muſt be uſed; firſt to ſtop, then to cure the malady, by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming thoſe they have miſ-guided; and, being now converted themſelves, to convert others alſo <hi>from the Error of their way, Jam.</hi> 5. 20. Briefly, where any hurt hath been done the Reputation, Fortunes, or Souls of men, the onely way one hath to Redeem his time is, as far as 'tis poſſible, to redeem his Guilt, and to recover his <hi>Innocence</hi> by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Compenſation he can, and by expreſſing his Zeal to Annihilate his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by making Amends for them.</p>
               <p>This was the Ground St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf went upon, when he Laboured ſo Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly after his Converſion. It was, to exterpate the falſe Principles he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated before, to ſatisfy the Church for the wrong he had done it, and by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Zeal for Chriſtianity, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare people for God in all parts of the world, wherever he could go. His great deſign was, to recover what he could of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150153:36"/>
time he had Loſt, while he was ſo ſtrict a <hi>Phariſee.</hi> And the ſame thing was the reaſon of thoſe ſeverities uſed in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ages; when Criminals were wont to inflict on themſelves great Penances; to macerate their bodies by hard Diſcipline; to give themſelves to auſtere Faſtings; to wallow on the ground; to cover themſelves with Sackcloth and Aſhes; to make Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acknowledgement of their offences; to throw themſelves at their fellow Chriſtians Feet, and upon their Knees to beg the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Good people at the Church doors; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us in his book of <hi>Repentance.</hi> Thoſe acts of mortification proceeded from a principle of Humility, and a deep ſenſe of ſin and of time miſ-ſpent; till ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on crept into the Church, and turned them into meer Pageantry: or the moſt uſeful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions we can gather from them is this; that to Redeem ones time to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, one right Chriſtian way is to make all poſſible amends and Reparation for evil actions, eſpecially ſuch evil actions as carry along with them <hi>Injury,</hi> and <hi>Scandal,</hi> beſides the Guilt which the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence contracted from the Sinfulneſs of their <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:150153:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A third way is, to do all the good one can.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> ANother way of Redeeming ones time is, <hi>to do all the good one can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To do Good, is to be truely Uſeful to others in his generation according to the Abilities God hath given him, and in that calling and <hi>Station</hi> wherein the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God hath diſpoſed of him. We all came into the World to ſerve God, and to help one another; nor have we any other buſineſs here. The <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world, that loſt not an hour of his life, <hi>went about doing good, Act.</hi> 10. 18. <hi>And thereby ſhewed, how unpardonable their Negligence is, who Triſle away their time, when they have ſo many objects of Charity before them, and thoſe whoſe Neceſſities are ſo great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150153:37"/>
Before I proceed upon this ſubject, we muſt obſerve, that a mans own neceſſities are to be regarded firſt. For Love to ones ſelf being the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Standard</hi> of that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we owe our Neighbours, it ought to have the Procedency, and to challenge the Principal ſhare of our time and Pains. And here we ſhould conſider our own wants duly. I do not mean our neceſſities as to the things of the World; in which reſpect mens wants are often as Imaginary, as their appetites are Inſatiable: but I ſpeak of <hi>Real</hi> neceſſities; thoſe of the Soul, which require our Conſtant and more Particular care, becauſe they are of the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and the hardeſt to be ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>We muſt begin with the <hi>Underſtanding;</hi> for the Notions which lodge there are the ſpring of action; and according as they are found or Rotten, ſo are our lives good or bad, and ſo is our time well or ill imployed. Great care therefore muſt be taken to have a right Judgment in all points (the firſt thing which the ſoul ſtands in ſuch need of.) And to do it ſubſtantial good in this reſpect, men ſhould ſedulouſly beſtow what fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities they have upon Contemplation, Reading, and Profitable ſtudies. For the ſoul Naturally is neither a Divine, nor <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> though indued with Faculties to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150153:37"/>
fit it for the Nobleſt ſpeculations. It muſt be under <hi>Pedagogy</hi> and <hi>Pupilage;</hi> nor can the Ripeſt years <hi>Manumit</hi> it from a ſtate of <hi>Tuition.</hi> Knowledge doth ſtill increaſe by the good Improvements we make of our hours; and this is the ſad reaſon of ſome mens Ignorance (eſpecially as to matters they ſhould know moſt of) becauſe the time they ſhould beſtow upon good books, they <hi>Dream</hi> away in ſloth, or <hi>Sin</hi> away in vice, or <hi>Fool</hi> away in ſports, and many childiſh <hi>Vanities,</hi> which they abuſively call, <hi>Diverſion;</hi> a word, which importeth <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> when indeed they will have <hi>none</hi> to be diverted <hi>from.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But a weak <hi>mind</hi> is not ſo bad as a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Temper.</hi> There are many Corruptions in the <hi>Lower</hi> faculties of the Soul, which greatly need an helping hand to cure; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravations of nature which are much the worſe, becauſe they make men like unto <hi>the very Beasts</hi> that periſh for want of <hi>mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> as well as of <hi>understanding.</hi> Here the way to do ones ſoul good indeed is, to cleanſe it from its vices; to govern its <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; to mortify its Luſts;</hi> to rectify its <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites;</hi> to wean it from <hi>Senſual Pleaſures;</hi> and to deſtroy that Malice, Envy, Pride, <hi>Revengefulneſs,</hi> and <hi>Implacability</hi> of <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> which make a man Reſemble, not ſo much a Brute, as the very Devil.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150153:38"/>
Theſe vices <hi>therefore</hi> are <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> things to imploy ones time upon; becauſe they are the things which bring the wrath of God upon the children of <hi>diſobedience;</hi> the things which <hi>Pollute the Conſcience,</hi> and coſt the Soul its peace in this life, and its <hi>Felicity</hi> in <hi>another; nay,</hi> the things which are not only the <hi>worſt</hi> for their effects, but the moſt <hi>Difficult</hi> alſo to be cured, becauſe they are rooted in the Heart; they are <hi>a Part of us;</hi> and it <hi>requires</hi> no little <hi>diligence Induſtry,</hi> and skill to be too Hard for <hi>Nature; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> when it comes to be <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> by <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> and when evil <hi>Inclinations</hi> are improved into a pernicious Habit.</p>
               <p>The truth is, if people would <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> their time well, they might find a great deal of work for themſelves at <hi>Home.</hi> Yet this muſt not <hi>ſuperſede</hi> the doing of good <hi>abroad too.</hi> There are Divers neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which God hath made us all Subject unto, that in ſome reſpect or other, each of us might be ſerviceable to his neighbours: and as various as theſe Neceſſities are, ſo various are the opportunities we have of diſpoſing our time to the beſt advantage, and after the moſt becoming manner. Eating and Drinking, and other ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are the life of <hi>Animals,</hi> whoſe end is deſtruction. The life of a man, (eſpecially of a <hi>Chriſtian)</hi> is to do good: this ſets him
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150153:38"/>
above all other Creatures here below, and makes him like unto the bleſſed God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whoſe goodneſs the whole earth is full of, and whoſe compaſſions fail not. To neglect this, is to throw aſide our great buſineſs for the ſake of mean employments, which will turn to no account, but to awaken our Conſciences hereafter, and to grieve us for our Folly, in flinging away that now, which our laſt Death-bed ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows will ſhew to have been of the higheſt Price.</p>
               <p>I Know, nature muſt be provided for, and that there are ſeveral Recreations which are Innocent in themſelves, and in their kind, neceſſary to preſerve us in health and vigour, that we may ſerve God, and ſpend our ſerious hours the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably. But how many unlawful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights are there, which ſhould have no part at all of our time allowed them? How many are there, which Border upon vice, ſo that little time cannot be afforded them without danger? How many that are the occaſions of ſin, though not vicious in their own Nature? and how many even of the moſt harmleſs ones, which are ſo inordinately purſued, that inſtead of being a Relaxation, they become a kind of Trade? ſhould an appeal be made to the conſcienc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Idle and vain perſons themſelves, they could not but confeſs, that much leiſure
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150153:39"/>
might be well ſpared for Pious, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table purpoſes, which there is no ſort of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for them to waſt other ways, but to take off that time which hangs upon their fingers. And yet to Redeem time, the greateſt remainder of it ſhould be beſtow'd upon doing of Good. <hi>There is one place of Scripcure that directs us, to break off our Sins by Righteouſneſs, and our Iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor,</hi> Dan 4. 27. meaning, that men ſhould make reparation for what is paſt, by doing eminent acts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> for the time to come. There is another place that tells us, <hi>He which converteth a Sinner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from death, and ſhall bide a multitude of ſins,</hi> Jerm. 5. 20. <hi>And there is a third place that ſaith of Charity in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that it ſhall cover a multitude of Sins,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 8. <hi>Now, though none of theſe Texts</hi> mean, <hi>that the doing of Good Juſtifies a man, or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitates his pardon, by any natural Cauſality, Efficiency, or virtúe of the work done</hi> (for that would be injurious to the doctrine of Gods free grace, and to our Saviours Merits and ſatisfaction) yet thus much they all imply, that for Chriſt's ſake, God is pleaſed of his own great goodneſs, to impute to us our good and charitable performances, and to accept them as the Condition and means of that pardon, which he freely gives unto all who bring forth fruits meet for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:150153:39"/>
This ſhews, That to do all the Good we can, is the ready way to redeem our Time effectually. Which yet is to be underſtood of <hi>increaſing</hi> our Diligence in doing what good we are able; ſo as to delight in it, and to make it the conſtant and urgent Buſineſs of that part of our Life which is left us. There is no recovering of our loſt Time, without doubling at leaſt our Labour and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. For Charity is a ſtanding Law of Chriſt; the great Rule we ſhould have all gone by, as ſoon as we were paſt the things of Children. At Twelve Years of Age the Lord Jeſus was found ſitting in the midſt of the Doctors, not ſo much to hear, as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them. It was his Father's Buſineſs, the neceſſary Work of doing Good he was then about. Which noble Example of Charity, teacheth all Mankind to begin <hi>betimes</hi> to do good Offices; and it upbraids us all with our Neglects, in loſing ſo many fair Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities we have had from our Youth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould remember our great Omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when we go about the Redeeming of our Time, becauſe thoſe we are to make compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for: And conſidering this cannot be done by that ordinary Zeal and Induſtry, which muſt have been expreſs'd, had we been uſeful in our Generation from the <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> it muſt needs be incumbent upon us to labour the more abundantly, to make up thoſe Defects, for which in Conſcience we are anſwerable. For in this caſe we are to conſider, what is our ſtanding Duty ſtill,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150153:40"/>
and what we are behind hand in: and to fill up the meaſure of our Good Works, we ſhould do as much in one Day, as might have taken up two, had we acted regularly all along. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs our Diligence be doubled, however we may be ſuppoſed, after our Repentance, to ſpend our Time well, we cannot be ſaid to <hi>redeem</hi> it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a great part of it is yet in <hi>Arrear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I obſerved before, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> compares our Chriſtian Progreſs to a Race; and that ſingle Compariſon will be enough to illuſtrate this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If the Combatants do not ſtart together; or, though they do, if all keep not on with equal Paces, Time and Ground will ſoon be loſt, tho' none of them come as yet to ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtraining for the Victory. The Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, that loyters away his Minutes; the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fler, that is willing to be diverted by imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Excurſions; and the unwary Wretch, that ſtrumble and falls by not looking to his Steps; Theſe ill Husbands of their Time, who might have finiſhed their Courſe laudably, by conſtant, treatable, and moderate ſtriving, having fallen much ſhort of the reſt by their own Tardineſs, are now under a great Neceſſity of exerting their utmoſt Strength and Vigour to <hi>recover</hi> their Minutes what they can; nor have they any other way left them, but to <hi>ſignalize</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by extraordinary Preſſings on, and by trying all their Abilities and Breath to the laft: Why, thus it is in our Chriſtian Courſe, in the Race that leadeth to Eternal Life, or Death. Some from the beginning run the way of God's
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150153:40"/>
Commandments with Patience, and Alacrity, and a conſtant Zeal: And happy are they who remember their Creator from the Days of their Youth; but theſe comparatively are but few. Others neglect the buſineſs of their Salvation, minding and loving the World only, as if they were to ſtay in it for ever. Others fly out into Extravagancies and Vanities, as the Devil or the Fleſh tempts them out of their way. Others fall into Apoſtacy from Truth and Religion; and of all theſe there is none that doth ſolid Good, nor is likely to come to Good, till either the Senſe of God's Goodneſs <hi>leads</hi> them, or the Fear of his Wrath and Juſtice <hi>drives</hi> them to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Conſidering therefore what Time they have loſt, and how nearly it concerns them to Redeem it, their only Courſe is, To gird up their Loins with Reſolution; to ſet about it with Vigour; to uſe their utmoſt Diligence; to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the more induſtriouſly; to abound in all manner of Good Works; and being converted themſelves, to apply all poſſible means to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their Brethren; as our Saviour told <hi>Peter</hi> in reference to the future Recovering himſelf from his Apoſtacy, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 32.</p>
               <p>And here People ſhould conſider well, what ſorts there are of Good Works, that they may be the better able to Redeem their Time, by doing Good indeed. As, to Inform and Teach the Ignorant, and put them in often remembrance of their Duty in all things; to admoniſh ſuch as do amiſs; to be great Examples of Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, and Sobriety; and by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150153:41"/>
Arts to promote the True Power, and the univerſal Practice of Religion; to reſtore the Good Name that was unjuſtly taken away; to make ample Reparation for all Violence and Fraud; and to do this readily and heartily, with the exemplary Zeal of <hi>Zachaeus,</hi> reſtoring Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold even for Falſe Accuſations. To rid ones Hands of Mammon gotten by Unrighteouſneſs, and to make Satisfaction for Wrongs and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; to forgive an Enemy; to vindicate the Innocent; to relieve the Oppreſſed; to help thoſe who are in Streights and Neceſſity; to comfort the Afflicted; to viſit the Fatherleſs and Widow in their Diſtreſs; to be Eyes to the Blind, and Feet to the Lame; to Feed the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and Cloath the Naked, and Aſſiſt the Sick; to Pray for all; and to reach out a kind Hand to all, occording as their Wants, and according as our Abilities and Opportunities are. This is to <hi>Do Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for the Redeeming of Time well, it is neceſſary for thoſe who have been ſlack, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of theſe main Offices, to <hi>heighten</hi> their Zeal in the Performance of them, to diſpatch them with a very quick Hand, and with a two-fold Expence of Induſtry and Labour; becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they cannot make up that Time which hath been loſt, nor compenſate for what they have been wanting in. For theſe things they ought to have done <hi>before;</hi> they would have been neceſſary Works, had they been very fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of their Hours; becauſe to do Good is a Law of Religion and Nature too, which bindeth
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150153:41"/>
perpetually. Now, as the Payment of a New Debt is no Diſcharge of an Old Arrear, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the doing of Good Offices at preſent a Defeiſance of former Obligations. The anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one's Duty at one time, is no Requital for Omiſſions at another, unleſs there be a large Supplement of Righteouſneſs and <hi>Charity.</hi> To uſe our Saviour's Words in another caſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. 23. <hi>Theſe things ought ye to have done, and not to leave the other undone.</hi> 'Tis this <hi>Addition</hi> of Induſtry and Zeal, which makes Men accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with God; as was obſerved before from that Rule, that is to be in the Day of Retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Laſt ſhall be as the Firſt, and the Firſt as the Laſt; that is, Every Man ſhall receive according to his Works: And that Peoples Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions may be the ſame, 'tis neceſſary there ſhould be the ſame Proportion of Good Works, either as to length of Time, or increaſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry: Labours in the Vineyard, if they be <hi>late,</hi> are to be <hi>double,</hi> to entitle the Workmen to an Equality of Reward; as was ſhewed par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly from the Inſtance of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more abundantly than the reſt, and thought himſelf obliged to do ſo, becauſe he had not been ſo early a Convert as others.</p>
               <p>When therefore you ſet your ſelf about this moſt neceſſary Work of Redeeming your Time, reflect upon your Life paſt, and conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, what Sins you have been guilty of; what ſorts of Righteouſneſs you have been moſt averſe to; what Duties you have been defective in; what fair Opportunities of doing Good you
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150153:42"/>
have wilfully omitted; and accordingly, apply your whole Mind, Strength and Soul to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of all thoſe Vertues, the Practice where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you have hitherto neglected; and purſue this Courſe with ſuch Reſolution, Conſtancy and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as if you were now to retrieve your Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Innocence; and as if you had no other Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in the World for the future, but to do all manner of Good to the utmoſt of your Power. <hi>Let him that ſtole ſteal no more,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 28: But that is not all: It follows, <hi>Rather let him labour, working with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth:</hi> You ſee, where Injuſtice hath abounded, there Induſtry and Charity muſt abound, and that much more; and ſo in all other Caſes, wherein a Man hath been either wanting, or exceſſive, he muſt attone for it by a moſt lively, operative, and earneſt Zeal to do all the Good he can, that he may be full of Good Works, though the Remainder of his Time be ſhort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:150153:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>IV. THE next Way of Redeeming your Time, is, <hi>Not to let any one Day ſlip away wholly, without promoting your Eternal Intereſt in ſome degree and meaſure.</hi> The wiſer and ſtricter ſort of Moraliſts among the Old Heathens, adviſed People to make choice of a Scheme of Vertue for the Rule of their Lives, and to order all their Actions according to it Day by Day. As thus; To begin their Works with earneſt Prayers to God; to honour God before all things; to have a Religious Regard for Oaths; to reverence their Parents; to love their Friends; to delight in good Men; to keep the Body, with all its Faculties and Deſires, in ſubjection; for very Shame to abſtain from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that is Evil, both abroad and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; to practice Vertue with Sincerity of Heart; to look upon Riches as a thing that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, and as ſuch to ſlight them; to ſtudy how to reſemble God in the Diſpoſitions of the Mind, and to make that ones Aim and Pleaſure; to be contented with ones Condition, and at all times to ſubmit to God's Providence, who often gives good Men theſe outward Matters with a ſparing Hand; to be inflexible and conſtant in a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Courſe; to weigh ones Actions well before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and to conſider the Nature and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150153:43"/>
of them; to obſerve Temperance and Moderation; to be meek, and patient, and juſt, and cautious in all caſes. Such Rules as theſe ſome old Moraliſts directed People to live by daily. And then, every Night before they went to ſleep, they directed them to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtrictly, how they had ſpent the Day; that, if they had lived according to Rule, they might have for their preſent Reward the Pleaſures and Joys of a Good Conſcience; but, if they had tranſgreſs'd, that they might repent, and thereby learn the better how to amend their Lives the Day following. To this end, before you take your Repoſe, ſay they, ask your ſelf, wherein you have tranſgreſs'd? What you have done? And ſo, look over all your Actions the Day paſt two or three times, that no one thing may eſcape Scruteny and Examination. This was great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, eſpecially for Heathens to give: And it brings to my remembrance, what <hi>Suetonius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, that good natur'd Prince, <hi>Titus,</hi> who for the Sweetneſs of his Temper was call'd, The Love and Delight of Mankind: Conſidering once, as he was at Supper, that he had not done that Day ſuch Acts of Kindneſs and Bounty as he was wont to do, ſaid, <hi>Diem perdidi, I have quite loſt this Day.</hi> Some <hi>Greeks</hi> that ſpeak of this Story, render his Saying thus, <hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> or, <hi>This Day I have not reigned;</hi> I have not been a Prince: As if all his Greatneſs conſiſted in doing Good daily, and as if he had thrown away his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Power, in ſuffering a Day to paſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome conſiderable Teſtimonies and Marks of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150153:43"/>
his Goodneſs. He remembred <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Rule of Self-examination at Night, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting for Failings: And however the Story be told, it comes all to one in effect: And no leſs a Man than St. <hi>Jerome</hi> takes particular Notice of it, in his Comments on the Sixth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and makes uſe of it to the Reproof and Shame of negligent Chriſtians. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Emperour</hi> Titus <hi>(a Man that was a Stranger to the Law, to the Goſpel, to the Doctrine of our Saviour and the Apoſtles, if he) was ſo concerned for the loſs of one Day, how ſhould not we be concern'd for the loſs of ſo many Days and Years too?</hi> And the Truth is, ſince Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt doth expect, that our Righteouſneſs ſhould exceed the Righteouſneſs even of the ſtricteſt Profeſſors among the Jews, (the Scribes and Phariſees) we cannot expect leſs than the greateſt Condemnation, if at laſt it cometh ſhort of the Righteouſneſs of Philoſophers and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. As we are under the Laws and Diſcipline of a Maſter, who is infinitely greater than a <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> or than <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf; ſo is our Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance and Diligence to be much greater than their Scholars was. The Covenant given us carries with it a Proſpect of far better things, than were manifeſtly and explicitly promiſed of old to the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves: And upon that account there is a Neceſſity for us to be the better Husbands of our Time, that we may obtain them.</p>
               <p>The Great Promiſe God hath given us, is, of Eternal Happineſs with himſelf; and to quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150153:44"/>
our Endeavours after it, theſe two things require our ſerious and <hi>daily</hi> Conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, What is neceſſary on our part in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Eternal Happineſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, How Aſſiduous and Conſtant our Care had need be, to do that daily which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably required of us; ſomething of it at leaſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then, the thing neceſſary on our Part, in order to Eternal Happineſs, is, a God-like <hi>Temper,</hi> and Diſpoſition of <hi>Mind.</hi> Though our Saviour hath purchaſed for us a <hi>Liberty</hi> to enter into that Holy and Bliſsful place above; yet to <hi>Prepare</hi> us for it, ſuch a Frame of Heart is requiſite, as will make it to us a place of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs <hi>indeed.</hi> Now that muſt needs be a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Frame; or a Temper ſuitable to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God. For we muſt not think that the meer Poſſeſſion of Heaven makes the Spirits of Men Happy; nor that a quiet Grief-leſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is that wherein all Felicity doth conſiſt. Happineſs, that is compleat and perfect, muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer all the Faculties of the Soul; eſpecially its Affections; and God muſt be the Glorious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for us to <hi>Enjoy;</hi> that is, to Admire, and Love, and delight in, to all Eternity. There muſt be therefore an Aſſimilation of Temper, and a likeneſs of Mind; becauſe Diſſimilitude naturally carries with it Diſplacency, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs, which is no more reconcilable with Happineſs, than Love is with Hatred. To live
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150153:44"/>
happily with God and Chriſt, we muſt be of the ſame Diſpoſitions; And it was for this great Reaſon, that when Chriſt lived with us upon Earth, he gave us ſo many Spiritual and Divine Laws. They were not purely Arbitrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, proceedings from God's abſolute and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controleable Pleaſure, meerly to try and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our Obedience; but they were intended as Wife and Gracious Methods, to Poliſh our Minds, to Perfect our Nature, and to raiſe it by degrees to ſuch an high and noble Pitch, that it might come near to the moſt Perfect and Bleſſed Nature of his Father, for the Fruition of whom he came to fit us.</p>
               <p>To anſwer therefore his great Ends, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for us to form in our Hearts a Divine Goodneſs of Temper, by the help of thoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts which he hath laid before us, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſomewhat like to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. when he laid before the Cattel pilled Rods, to make them conceive Lambs of a ſuitable Colour. Thoſe Divine Rules which are propoſed to us to obſerve, are to make us Partakers of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; to renew in us the Divine Image; to ſhape in our Souls a Reſemblance of God; and all this, that we may be meet for the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in Light; becauſe without ſuch a Similitude, it is impoſſible for us, either to pleaſe God, or to be pleaſed with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe things being throughly conſidered, it will manifeſtly appear, in the ſecond place, that we are ſtrictly concern'd to make diligent
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150153:45"/>
and daily uſe of our Time, to do what is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary towards our everlaſting Happineſs. For it is a thing of no ſudden diſpatch; but that which requires all the time a Man can find in his whole Life, to do it well. Thoſe Moral Vertues which ſerve to perfect us, and to make us like unto God, are not poured out all in an inſtant, as thoſe miraculous Gifts were of Old; much leſs can they become preſently habitual. There is required a conſtant Courſe of repeated Actions to acquire and fix them; and this requires Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity of Practice: Day by Day, ſome part or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this neceſſary Work muſt be diſpatch'd: Otherwiſe the Difficulties of it will increaſe; in <hi>This</hi> reſpect like ſecular buſineſs, which when it comes in upon us in abundance, grows under our hands by being neglected, though but for a Day.</p>
               <p>In the proſecution of this Matter, let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what labour the very <hi>Beginnings</hi> call for. The firſt Task we are to go about is, to rectifie our Corrupt Nature; which is a thing that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to continual attendance and care over it, becauſe it is like a ſort of Soyl, which is ſtill apt of it ſelf to run to Weeds, even without our watering. We brought with us from the Womb the Seminal Principles of Evil. And as theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear betimes, ſo they riſe quickly to a great head, and heighth, like Nettles and ſuch other Traſh, which taint the Ground ſtill the more, by caſting new Seeds for their Propagation. Here then the Work ſhould be early, for the ſaving of time; to cultivate our Nature from
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150153:45"/>
our Youth, with a quick hand to check thoſe Vices, which are like Poyſonous Weeds in us; and to make all the Trumpery to Dye daily, as the Man grows. Pride, Anger, Spightfulneſs, Envy, Luſt, Senſuality, Inordinate Self-Love, Roughneſs, and Intractability of Spirit, and whatever comes under the notion of <hi>ill Nature;</hi> theſe are very Noxious things, that ſpring out of us, and that ſtain and vitiate the whole Man more and more daily; and therefore require con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Diligence to extirpate them what we can, while the Mind is yet ſoft, tender and pliant: Becauſe when once the Devil irrigates, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom confirms them, they will be the harder and harder to be Eradicated. Many a Soul is ſpoil'd and ruin'd for want of good Education in time. The Practice of Sin brings Delight with it; Pleaſure makes it Cuſtomary; Cuſtom renders it habitual; and when that which was a Fault, comes to be Wickedneſs; (ſtudied, acted, repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Vice, and deeply Rooted;) the labour in clearing the Soul of it, will be as different in proportion, as it is between drawing a little Shrub, and grubbing up a ſturdy Tree.</p>
               <p>This confirms the Matter we are now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> that in new moulding our Hearts to fit our ſelves for Eternal Felicity, we ſhould redeem our time by doing ſomething <hi>every day</hi> that is conſiderable. For the time we <hi>Loſe,</hi> or <hi>Neglect,</hi> Vice <hi>Gains;</hi> and thereby becomes the more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be ſubdued and mortified. <hi>Can the</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopian <hi>change his Skin, or the</hi> Leopard <hi>his Spots? Then may ye alſo do good, that are accuſtomed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150153:46"/>
to do Evil, Jer.</hi> 13. 23. To break an habit, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially on a ſudden, is like the invading and forcing of Nature, which is not to be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Violent</hi> hand. Whether it be in a Good, or in an Evil courſe of Life, the Powers of the Soul gather ſtrength by exerciſe and uſe; but much more in an evil Courſe; becauſe our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Senſes being thereby wont to be gratified, fall into a confederacy with our inward Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and between both, Reaſon finds it a very hard matter to keep it ſelf from being Captivated. Upon which account it muſt needs require Time, to recover that Dominion which is its Right and Prerogative. And though Grace comes in to its aſſiſtance, yet conſidering that the Spirit of God worketh in a moral way, by exciting, moving, and perſwading, but not conſtraining, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt cannot be preſent and inſtantaneous. For as long as Nature is at the bottom, it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and that with Vigour, when it hath the aid and help of Senſe, and when cuſtom hath given it a kind of Title to the Maſtery. This ſhews what great Neceſſity there is for a Man, to beſtow pains upon himſelf <hi>Daily;</hi> becauſe it is this which will give him a gradual Victory: He is continually doing ſomething <hi>Towards</hi> it: Here he gaineth one Point, and there another, and ſo in time he finds certain and kindly ſucceſs, by thus taming his Nature, and bringing it to a ductile manageable Temper by degrees.</p>
               <p>All this while I ſuppoſe him not to have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to the pitch of an over-grown Sinner, but to be come to the ordinary Age of Manhood;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150153:46"/>
when ones Luſts, though they are ſtrong and impetuous, yet are not ſo Fixt, Obſtinate, and Refractory, as crooked Old Age is apt to make them. Such an <hi>Experienced</hi> Wretch, whom the Pleaſure, and perhaps the Profit likewiſe of ſo many Years hath confirm'd in Wickedneſs, comes at laſt to be ſo hardned, that all Reaſonings, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, Counſels, and Prayers are thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon him, and make as little effectual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon his perverſe Mind, as they would upon a Rock, or Adamant. The danger of coming to this ſad paſs, is a <hi>ſtronger</hi> Argument ſtill of the Neceſſity there is to redeem ones time, by doing ſomething <hi>Daily</hi> in order to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; that is, to mortifie ſome Luſt or other every day, and every day to live more and more unto God. <hi>For when Luſt hath conceived it bringeth forth Sin, Jam.</hi> 1. 15. and Sin is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd by degrees, by growing, and gathering ſtrength daily. And by this means the Devil inſenſibly prepares a way to that ſad State, which Divines call <hi>Final Impenitence;</hi> meaning ſuch a Numbneſs, Stupidity, and Deadneſs of Heart, as doth utterly indiſpoſe it for a true Godly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. 'Tis to be fear'd, that Men often come to this wretched State by the juſt Judgment of God upon them; for their irreligious lives, and for their obſtinately putting off the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them from <hi>Day to Day:</hi> The truth is, it naturally followeth ſuch a wicked Courſe: For <hi>Uſe</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom</hi> do naturally ſerve to harden the Heart, as was obſerved before: So that when the Hoary Head comes, it is as hard a matter to renew that old wicked Mind in it, as it is to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150153:47"/>
renew ones Age. Nature is of it ſelf inclined to Evil; and when a long trade of Wickedneſs hath brought the Mind to be in love with it, to be devoted to it, to be bent, ſet, and fixt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, it muſt needs be morally impoſſible to pluck up thoſe Men's Habits quite by the Roots, which have been ſo many Years a contracting, and which have grown ſo ſtrong and deep into the very <hi>Heart.</hi> So that though we ſhould ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an old Villain to have the ſame means and meaſures of Grace which are afforded the <hi>Vain</hi> Youth, that perhaps is guilty of the ſame Sins too; yet the caſe of the former would be far more deſperate than the condition of the latter, were there nothing elſe to be conſidered but this, becauſe the one hath been much more <hi>Uſed</hi> and <hi>Accuſtomed</hi> to Wickedneſs than the other.</p>
               <p>But beſides this, it muſt be ſaid, that the Hopes concerning both are not the ſame. For the more time Men waſte in an Evil Courſe, the leſs they have of God's Spirit; and by this means alſo the ſtiffer and harder are their Hearts, and the more they Sin away their day of Grace. Without Chriſt we can do nothing, <hi>Jo.</hi> 15. 5. <hi>For it is God which worketh in us, both to will, and to do, of his good Pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2. 13. The Strength we have, is from above; the Power which ſerves to prepare and aſſiſt our Souls, and which doth every way enable us to work out our Salvation, it is freely given by the Father of Spirits. Now though God giveth freely unto all, and to every Man ſuch a portion of his Grace as is neceſſary and ſuitable; yet
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150153:47"/>
they that are negligent, and ill Husbands of their Talents, do impair their Stock daily: By reſiſting the Holy Ghoſt, they take a Courſe to <hi>grieve</hi> him; and by continuing to <hi>grieve,</hi> they proceed at length to <hi>quench</hi> him. Where God's Grace is abus'd or ſlighted, there he withdraws it, in Vengeance for that Wilfulneſs and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which was antecedent: And then is God ſaid, to give People up unto their own Hearts Luſts; to let them walk in their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81. 12. to ſend them ſtrong Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo that they believe a Lie, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 11. to give them up to vile Affections, and to give them over to a reprobate Mind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 26, 28. The Meaning of theſe Expreſſions is, That God doth ſometimes take away from Men the Grace they had; that he quite leaves them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and delivers them up to the ſaddeſt ſtate of Mind; thereby puniſhing them moſt juſtly for the long Incorrigibleneſs of their Temper. By this means 'tis poſſible for them to play and ſin away all the accepted Time before they are aware, and to bring themſelves under an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſible Sentence of Damnation in this their Life-time. It is <hi>poſſible,</hi> I ſay; and 'tis to be fear'd many actually <hi>do</hi> ſo, by perſiſting and going on in a Trade of Wickedneſs from Year to Year. I anſwer, 'tis a juſt <hi>Provocation</hi> for God to deal by them, as he did by <hi>Pharaob,</hi> whom he gave utterly over to an obdurate ſtate for his Stubbornneſs and Obſtinacy, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the Sixth Plague. And though he did not preſently cut him off, but ſuffer'd him to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150153:48"/>
live ſtill ſome time longer; yet this was not in expectation of Repentance from him, being now brought by his own Wilfulneſs to a deſerted Condition; but it was to this end, that he might be made at laſt a ſignal and aſtoniſing Example of Divine Vengeance. From which Inſtance it is clear, that a Man may ſin away his Time, and the Grace of God, till he comes to an Incapacity of repenting in good earneſt; and that he may do this before he dies.</p>
               <p>And this is one Reaſon, why the beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines are ſo ſevere againſt that which they call a <hi>Late Repentance;</hi> meaning, Remorſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and Sorrow for Sin, which is not <hi>begun</hi> till old Age, or Sickneſs comes, and the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Death with it. For though it be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God pardons every True Penitent, whenever he turns to God with all his Heart and Soul: Yet the great Queſtion is, Whether a late Repentance be True, Right, and ſuch as the Goſpel requires? that is, Whether it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a True Change, and Renovation of the Mind? For there may be a Sorrow, and often is, a real and paſſionate Sorrow, without ſuch a Change; a Sorrow that proceeds, not from an Hatred of Sin, but meerly from a Fear of Hell.</p>
               <p>This is clear from the Practice of many Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and Unrighteous Hypocrites, who in time of ſudden and dangerous Sickneſs ſighed and groan'd, have been reſtleſs and in an Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150153:48"/>
ſent in all haſte for a Confeſſor, call'd for Prayers, and expreſs'd ſuch Griefs, Vows, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and Reſolutions of Amendment, as if they were as right Penitents, as that dying Thief was upon his Croſs; and yet upon the Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their Health, have dropt the Memory of all theſe Saint-like Profeſſions, left all their Vows behind them in their Chambers, taken up again their former Courſes, returned like Dogs to the Vomit they had caſt up, to the ſame Riot, Rapine, Injuſtice and Malice which they acted before. This is a Sign, that all that while the Love of Sin lay lurking and cloſe in their Breaſts, unrenounc'd, unmoleſted; and that all the Bitterneſs of their Souls came only from the Fear of Damnation; a Paſſion, ſomewhat like that of Criminals, when they are going to be Hang'd, and yet, if they had Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, would be as diſhoneſt as ever under the very Gibbet. Now for Wicked Men to be in a Fright, when they think themſelves a Dying, is no wonder at all, eſpecially if their Conſciences be awake. And if Fear and Sorrow be all, it is as good as nothing, though it be hearty and paſſionate: For the Devil is a Devil ſtill, tho' he believes and trembles; and perhaps thoſe Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Mind are no better than <hi>his,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wicked <hi>Men</hi> are ruffled on their Sick Beds, eſpecially after a long Life, a continual Courſe, a conſtant Trade of Impiety and Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For how is it probable, that ſo many old beloved Vices can be quite caſt off on a ſudden? That ſo many fixt Habits can be eradicated in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150153:49"/>
the twinkling of an Eye? Or that the whole Bent and Temper of the Heart can in a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be changed ſo, as to be Diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to what it was juſt before the Phyſician was ſent for? No; it is far more probable, that it was only the ſight of Hell that ſcared the Wretch, and threw him into Pangs; and ſo any Man may be troubled, terrified and tormented, though God hath forſaken him; becauſe Self-preſervation is an inſeparable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reſult and Summ of this whole Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this; That to redeem ones Time to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good purpoſe, it is an excellent way to be bettering ones Spiritual State <hi>every Day</hi> in ſome reſpect and proportion. For the Work a Man hath to do is great and difficult, and that which requires every Day's Care and Diligence of him; eſpecially if Evil Cuſtoms have got the Start, and are before-hand with him. Nature <hi>alone</hi> is hard to be rectified; and a conſtant Tenor of Diligence is neceſſary to transform it ſo, as to make it repreſent the Divine Nature. But when Evil <hi>Habits</hi> are to be contended and grapled with <hi>too,</hi> every Day's Reſolution and Activity is little enough to conquer them as they ſhould be conquer'd, that Faith and Vertue may carry the Day, and triumph over them. Either they muſt be daily reſiſted, or moſt certainly they will get Ground of us daily: And what Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Negligence will turn to at laſt, in Old Age, or upon a Death-Bed, God alone know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150153:49"/>
infallibly. 'Tis not likely a Man ſhould be able to deſtroy that at his laſt Hour, or in the time of Weakneſs, which he ſuffer'd to gather and grow to a great Head in the Days of Health and Vigour. More likely it is, that God will puniſh ſuch Negligence with utter Dereliction and Hardneſs of Heart; againſt which no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient or ſure Proviſion can be made, but by hearkning to his Voice, while it is called <hi>to Day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remember therefore the Advice even of thoſe old Philoſophers I ſpake of, who would have you reſolve and fix upon a good Rule of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, (and none can pretend to be ſo good, as what Jeſus Chriſt hath given us all) and every Day examine your Conſciences what you have omitted, and what you have done; what Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers you have offer'd up unto the Father of Lights; what Offices of Righteouſneſs, Mercy and Goodneſs you have performed to Men; what Good you have done to your own Souls; what inordinate and irregular Deſires you have cheriſh'd; what Luſts of the Fleſh you have mortified; what Paſſions you have commanded and ſubdued; how low you have brought every lofty Imagination; how far you have put away all Bitterneſs, and Wrath, and Anger, and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and Evil-ſpeaking, with all Malice; wherein ye have imitated the Life of our Lord Jeſus, who ſacrificed His for you; and to what Degrees you have perfected your Nature unto a Similitude of the adorable Perfections of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150153:50"/>
ever-bleſſed God, whoſe great and tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are over all his Works. As true Honour doth conſiſt, not in an empty Title, but in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and Nobleneſs of Mind; ſo doth true Religion conſiſt, not in formal Shows and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, but in thoſe Divine Endowments of Soul, which make us approach near to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our Maker. And by taking your ſelf thus to Account every Night, you will the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcern what you are to implore God's Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Aſſiſtance for againſt the Day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; wherein you have been wanting; what Defects you are to make up; what is to be the principal Buſineſs of the next Day; what Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces you are to improve; what you are to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and what you are to avoid. In ſhort; you will eaſily know how, and be eaſily able in deed to redeem you loſt Time; becauſe it will be <hi>little,</hi> if due Care and Diligence be uſed <hi>every Day.</hi> By this Method you may ſoon take an honeſt Account of your Actions; your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance will be renewed day by day, the <hi>Care</hi> you ought to have of your Immortal Soul will continually abide with you, and reſt upon your Mind; your Heart and Ways will be always under your <hi>own</hi> watchful Eye as well as God's; the Aſſiſtances and Comforts of God's Spirit you will never be without; there will be no room for thoſe vicious Habits, which bring others at laſt to a moral Impoſſibility of repenting; 'twill be impoſſible for them ever to be ſixt, or to take Root; hardly will an Hour in any one Day be quite loſt; I am ſure, a long Tract of Time
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150153:50"/>
Time will be ſaved, which is utterly dropt and forgotten by thoſe, who leave all to the ſad After-reckonings of a Death-bed. The great Miſchief then is, that 'tis out of their Power to recover their Loſſes, though their Hearts ſhould earneſtly deſire it; ſo many Months and Years are impoſſible to be recalled; and all this Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity comes from the want of ſome Diligence <hi>every Day;</hi> 'tis Men's great Negligence as to this Particular, that poſtpones the whole Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Salvation, and hinders that affidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Progreſs and Proficiency, whereby otherwiſe they might have grown in Grace unto a perfect Man, unto the Meaſure of the Stature of the Fulneſs of Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:150153:51"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>V. and ANother Effectual Way of Redeem-Laſtly. Aing our Time, is, <hi>To ſpend as much, as may be, of the remainder of it upon Devotion, eſpecially upon the Solemnities of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Devotion in the Houſe of God. A Day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand,</hi> ſaith the devout Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 10. It is better ſpent, and will turn to better Account, than all the Years that Vice and Vanities conſume. To withdraw our ſelves from the World; to take away, as it were by Repriſal, that Time which the World uſually ſteals from us; to Dedicate, Offer up, Appropriate that Time to God, and to beſtow it upon God: This is ſuch a plain way to recover our loſt Hours, as is obvious to all who have a true Senſe of Religion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are many Duties which we own in the Theory to be Good, and yet are wanting to in point of Practice, to encourage our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours as to this Particular, Two Things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire our ſerious Conſideration.</p>
               <p n="1">I. Firſt, That to attend diligently upon the Ordinances and Inſtitutions of our Religion, is an excellent way for us to do the Great Work for which the redeeming of our beſt Time is <hi>preſcrib'd</hi> and <hi>intended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:150153:51"/>
II. Secondly, That it is a ready way to keep us from loſing our time for the <hi>Future.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, To attend diligently upon the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Inſtitutions of our Religion, is an excellent way for us to do that great Work, for which the Redeeming of our <hi>Loſt</hi> time is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and <hi>Intended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Ordinances of our Religion I mean, the Liſtning to and Meditating upon the Word of God; the uſe of the holy Sacrament; and the lifting up of our Hearts in Prayers and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, and the like. And by the great Work we are to do I underſtand, the preparing and fitting our Souls for a Bleſſed Eternity. Now for the effectual doing of this, nothing ſerveth as a more proper and direct means, than dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent attendance upon thoſe Religious Offices.</p>
               <p>For it is by the conſtant uſe of theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that the Spirit of God is Miniſtred unto us, and worketh in us; that our Luſts are gradually mortified; that our Hearts are transform'd and changed as God would have them; that the Virtues which are neceſſary to qualifie us for an heavenly State, are confirm'd and increaſed in us; and that we grow in Grace, and in the ſaving knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. To illuſtrate this Matter particularly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> Rom. 10. 17. Whether this Word
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150153:52"/>
be Preach'd, or Read, it is an inſtrument of Grace to all whoſe Hearts are open to receive and obey it. Therein the moſt precious <hi>Promiſes</hi> are exhibited, and the moſt terrible <hi>Threats</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt all Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Men; eſpecially againſt ſuch as hold the Truth in unrighteouſneſs. Therein all thoſe <hi>Doctrines</hi> are contained, which are according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to godlineſs; the whole Counſel of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared; and all thoſe Things revealed, which are profitable for inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, that every Man may be perfect, throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good Works. Therein are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe divine <hi>Laws,</hi> which are apt to renew our Minds, and to cleanſe us from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, that we may perfect Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the fear of God: Therein alſo we ſee a great cloud of <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> who by their Exemplary Lives have taught us to lay aſide every weight, and the Sin that doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and to run with patience the Race that is ſet before us. Above all, therein we behold the <hi>Example</hi> of the Lord Jeſus, whoſe moſt holy Life was intended for a Pattern unto us, that we ſhould follow his ſteps; and whoſe ignominious and moſt painful Death was intended partly to <hi>Frighten</hi> us from Sin, that he might redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie to himſelf a peculiar People, zealous of good Works. All theſe things we find in the Scriptures; and by theſe means the Scriptures, if duly conſidered and meditated upon, are of vaſt uſe to us, and ſerve to produce in us Faith, Hope, Charity, and all manner of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150153:52"/>
and true Holineſs. Upon which account it muſt needs be a very neceſſary and profitable way of Redeeming our Time, to beſtow as much of it as we can upon Learning, Hearing, Reading, and inwardly digeſting the good word of God, which is thus able in all reſpects to ſave our Souls.</p>
               <p>In like manner, the frequent <hi>Participation</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>Body and Blood</hi> is a vaſt help towards thoſe Spiritual improvements, which ſhould take up the greateſt part of our time. For as that heavenly Ordinance puts us in mind of God's adorable Perfections; eſpecially his Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs and Mercy, which ſhined ſo bright in the complicated Myſtery of our Redemption; ſo it ſerves to raiſe our Hearts into the higheſt Admirations of God; and ſtirs us up to ſtand in awe of his Juſtice; to rely upon his Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; to expreſs all poſſible Gratitude for Mercies ſo undeſerved, ſo ſtupendious; to ſubmit with all Humility to his Commands and Providence; to ſhew the Senſe we have of his great Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by ſuitable returns of Affection; and to love one another, becauſe God hath ſo loved us all. In ſhort, by preparing our ſelves duly for this Bleſſed Sacrament, and by a Reverent and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious uſe of it, our Faith becomes the ſtronger, our Hopes the more vigorous; our Charity the more Ardent; our Minds the more Circumſpect; our Care and Caution the more ſtrict; and all the ordinary Gitfs and Graces of God's Spirit are thereby the more Exerciſed, Confirmed, and increaſed in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:150153:53"/>
This ſhews what an admirable way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming our loſt time this is, to attend diligently upon the Inſtitutions of our Religion, becauſe the great work we are to do, in order to a bleſſed Eternity, and to fit us for it, is thereby carried on with conſtant Diſpatch, and with the quicker Hand. But we ſhould conſider moreover how profitably we may employ our time, and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſome meaſure what is loſt, by daily ſetting aſide ſome part and portion of the time we have for the <hi>Ordinance of Prayer alone;</hi> even when we are not Communicants at the Altar, nor hearers of the Word after the moſt ſolemn man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Every day will I bleſs thee,</hi> ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145. 2. And indeed the thing is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon an eternal Law of Reaſon: For we ſtand in <hi>Need</hi> of his Goodneſs, and <hi>Receive</hi> of his Goodneſs daily; and therefore it is neceſſary and equal, that we ſhould addreſs our ſelves to him daily, with Supplications and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Now if we would do this (I mean, do it with ſuch devout Hearts as ought to be applied to ſo ſublime a Duty) beſides the advantage we get by attending Weekly and Monthly upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinances, our daily attendance upon <hi>This,</hi> would be of infinite uſe to us. For hereby we do not only fit and prepare our Souls for an heavenly State, but are indeed a <hi>Doing</hi> the works of Heaven; actually fix'd upon them, already imployed and <hi>Engaged</hi> in thoſe Exerciſes, which are the Life of Angels, and of the Spirits of Juſt Men made Perfect. To admire, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150153:53"/>
and love; and praiſe God, is the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buſineſs of the Bleſſed above: And this we do here below, though not in that intenſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, when we worſhip him in Truth, and in the Beauty of Holineſs; when we proſtrate our ſelves before him, under a profound and awful Senſe of his ſuper-excellent Majeſty; when our Minds are fix'd upon him, as the Glorious and Raviſhing Object of our Contemplations; when the Faculties of our Souls are acting vigorouſly upon him; when we Exalt and Magnifie him in our Hearts; when our Deſires ſtream out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, as the only Good we long for; when our Thoughts are full of rapturous Idea's of his Perfections; when we celebrate and ſet him forth, as the greateſt, wiſeſt, and beſt of all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; when our Hearts are inflamed with the Love of him; and when we offer up our Prayers and Praiſes to him with Affections as high as Heaven, and as large as the Univerſe.</p>
               <p>And can any time be better, or ſo well ſpent, as that which is thus employed? This is to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem ones Time to the beſt purpoſe; and in ſome Senſe to live it over again, by following the great Work of ones whole life cloſe, and ſo by living much in a little: And the deſign of this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is, to ſtir you up to the Love and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Devotion; as a proper way of making your Life up, wherein ſoever you may have been hitherto defective. To recover what hath been miſ-ſpent, and to fit your ſelf for God and Heaven, without frequent Acts of Piety, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible:
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150153:54"/>
Rather it is a way to loſe on, and ſpend amiſs ſtill, and to make your Condition every day worſe and worſe. And this is one great Reaſon, that there are ſo many Evil Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the World, becauſe they neglect a Courſe of Devotion, which, if diligently and rightly followed, could not chuſe but make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>I do not mean, that every one is a Saint that reſorts to the Church, or that the repeating of ſo many good Prayers is enough to diſpoſe and qualifie People for Eternal Happineſs. No, there are ſome that content themſelves with the bare performance of the outward Work; and there are others that go to the Temple ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in compliance with a Cuſtom, or out of Compliment and Civility to the Laws, than for Conſcience ſake towards God. But this is my meaning, that when Men apply their Souls to the uſe of God's Ordinances, as a neceſſary <hi>Duty,</hi> and ſeriouſly <hi>intend</hi> to do themſelves good by the uſe of them, and go about it with Sincerity of <hi>Mind,</hi> and Exerciſe themſelves in it with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive <hi>Zeal,</hi> and with Humble, Fervent and Devout Spirits; when their Hearts are thus <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly</hi> diſpos'd, they take ſuch a ready Courſe to fit themſelves for Heaven, as God will be ſure to Bleſs and Proſper with ſucceſs, if they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere unto the end in ſo doing. They are then in God's way, and in the way of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to enlighten their Underſtandings, to guide them into the Truth, to renew their Minds, to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150153:54"/>
ſanctifie their Affections, to direct their Wills, to improve and perfect their Natures, and to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen them unto every good work. And by this means, as they obtain pardon for their paſt Miſcarriages, ſo they gradually retrieve their former Loſſes, and make the time paſt their own again, by their extraordinary Husbandry of the remainder, and by filling up an <hi>Hiatus</hi> with a proportionable Supplement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, As the diligent attendance upon God's Ordinances helps us to redeem the time that is <hi>Gone;</hi> ſo it ſerves to keep us from <hi>Loſing</hi> more for the <hi>Future.</hi> We may reckon that time to be <hi>Loſt,</hi> which is ſpent either after a <hi>Wicked,</hi> or after a <hi>Vain</hi> manner: That is, when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience contracteth ſome great Guilt in the ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, or when the Man gets no ſolid Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or Satisfaction by it, though ſtrictly ſpeaking we cannot affirm, it is ſinned away; and in both theſe reſpects we ſhall ſee, that a courſe of Devotion ſecures us from being any conſiderable Loſers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, That time is to be accounted <hi>Loſt,</hi> which is ſpent in <hi>Wickedneſs.</hi> When Vice takes it up, ſo much of our Life is gone to our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Prejudice and Hurt, unleſs the Wickedneſs be retracted by timely Repentance: And when it is retracted, a Man doth what he can to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do his Actions, and to unlive his former Life; and ſo begins, as it were, his days again. To be ſure he himſelf reckons ſo much of his time
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150153:55"/>
quite thrown oway; is willing to raſe it out of his own Memory; and heartily wiſheth, that the juſt Judge of all the Earth would forget it too, and never impute or account it unto him. Now People that are ever mindful of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, are not in danger of loſing their time <hi>This</hi> way; becauſe they are aſſured, that if they <hi>regard Iniquity in their Hearts, the Lord will not hear them.</hi> Pſal. 66. 18. Nay, that their <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will be an Abomination,</hi> Prov. 15. 8. Upon which account 'tis morally impoſſible for them to Sin and Pray too, leſt inſtead of Mercies they ſhould draw down a Thunderbolt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Bread</hi> ſhould receive a <hi>Stone,</hi> or a <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion.</hi> They who have a ſenſe of God, muſt needs be ſhie of offering up ſuch Prayers, as are enough to put them out of Countenance, and out of Hope too; ſuch Prayers as they know will Recoil upon them; and not only fly in their faces, but terrifie and gall their very Conſciences alſo. But in truth, we cannot ſuppoſe Men of Pious Minds to ſpend their precious Time to ſuch bad purpoſes as theſe; becauſe the Notions they have of God's Majeſty, of his Omnipreſence and Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, of his Juſtice, Holineſs, and the like, are a continual check upon them, to govern their natural Inclinations, and to reſtrain them from thoſe evil Courſes, into which others run with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fear or Wit, <hi>as the Horſe ruſheth into the Battel,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 6. Beſides, as they have not the <hi>Heart,</hi> or <hi>Face</hi> to Sin, ſo neither have they thoſe <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities,</hi> which the Devil Miniſtreth daily to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150153:55"/>
thoſe who are ſuch <hi>Strangers</hi> to the Throne of Grace, as if they lived <hi>Without</hi> God in the World. Such Men are never out of the Devil's road; and therefore it is no wonder if Vice be the trade they beſtow their Time upon; no wonder, if a Luxurious Table, or a <hi>Dalilah</hi>'s Lap, or a Drunken Society, or Prophane Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or the ſtudy of Miſchief, or the Drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery of Covetouſneſs, or the Pride of Life taketh up thoſe Hours which God hath a right to. Ungodly Principles and Contempt of things Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, do always betray Men to ſome wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or other; nor cannot be but Irreligion and Vice muſt go together; ſo that 'mongſt other Arguments that might be heaped up to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to a life of Devotion, this is one, that it is an excellent <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Preſervative</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, and keeps us out of Harms-way: <hi>Bleſſed is the Man,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, that walketh not in the Counſel of the Ungodly, nor ſtandeth in the way of Sinners, nor ſitteth in the Seat of the Scornful,</hi> Pſ. 1. 1. This is the Felicity of the devout Man in particular; whoſe Affections be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet upon the things above, he has not ſo much time to ſpare from Prayer and Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, as the Children of this World fling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon their Luſts; nor doth Temptation or ill Company ſeduce him into the ways of Death. The Angels of God are his guard to keep him in all his ways. Solitude, which is to ſome a <hi>Snare,</hi> is to him an opportunity for Grave and Holy <hi>Meditations.</hi> This Houſe of God is a Sanctuary to him from his own <hi>Evil
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150153:56"/>
Self;</hi> a place of refuge from his corrupt Heart; the very <hi>Thoughts</hi> whereof he there keeps in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by minding the ſeveral Duties of the Place, and by the reverend Apprehenſions he hath of that infinite Being, who is the <hi>Searcher</hi> of Hearts, and by this means he clears and rids his Soul of thoſe vagrant Imaginations, which otherwiſe would diſturb and annoy his Heart, as <hi>Abraham</hi> drove away the <hi>Fowls,</hi> when he offer'd to God <hi>His</hi> Sacrafice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 11.</p>
               <p>Thus, to attend diligently upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Inſtitutions of our Religion, keeps us from loſing more of our Time in the <hi>Firſt</hi> reſpect; from ſquandering it away upon that which is <hi>Evil;</hi> nay, from laying any part of it out upon the <hi>Principles,</hi> the <hi>Occaſions,</hi> the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities</hi> of Evil. And the uſe we ſhould make of it is, that of that little Time God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots us in this World, we ſhould ſet what we can apart for religious Offices. The Scripture calls it, <hi>Praying without Ceaſing,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5. 17. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in Prayer, and watching in the ſame with Thankſgiving,</hi> Col. 4. 2. <hi>Praying always with all Prayer and Supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all Perſeverance,</hi> Epheſ. 6. 18. <hi>And continuing inſtant in Prayer,</hi> Rom. 12. 12. By which Expreſſions is meant, not that we ſhould be praying every <hi>Minute</hi> of the Day (for other Works of Neceſſity and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are to be attended on alſo) but that we ſhould not let ſlip any convenient <hi>Opportunity</hi> of Devotion, nor play away thoſe hours which are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150153:56"/>
                  <hi>Proper</hi> for it; but with all poſſible diligence and application of Mind obſerve thoſe times of Prayer which are <hi>Stated</hi> and <hi>Fixt,</hi> either by publick Authority, or by our own private, voluntary choice; ſo that our whole time may turn to very good account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, By this means we ſhall be ſure not to ſpend our Time <hi>Vainly</hi> neither; which is <hi>another</hi> way of loſing it; that is, when a Man gets no ſolid <hi>Benefit</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> by it, though ſtrictly ſpeaking we cannot affirm, that he <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> it away, or lays it out upon Vice and Wickedneſs. Man being a rational Creature, endued with Underſtanding, on purpoſe that he might deliberately Act in order to Ends that befit and become the Dignity of his Nature; all that time is to be reckon'd <hi>Loſt</hi> to him, which doth not ſerve in ſome meaſure to <hi>Anſwer</hi> ſuch Ends. To gratifie the Senſes is the life of a Beaſt; and it becomes a Beaſt well enough; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Beaſt hath no higher, or nobler Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties than Senſe. But in <hi>Man,</hi> Reaſon hath the Superiority; or a faculty of diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that which is morally Good, or morally Evil; and a power of diſcourſing and judging touching the <hi>Nature</hi> of his Actions; what they <hi>Deſerve,</hi> and what may be the <hi>Rewards</hi> of them. To Act like a <hi>Man</hi> therefore, is to live according to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> or, as it becomes a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that hath the rules of Vertue and Religion before him; and as long as he Acteth according to thoſe Rules, <hi>beſides</hi> the Rewards he Entitles
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150153:57"/>
himſelf to in <hi>another</hi> World hereafter, he doth himſelf great good in this Life, and receives that <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of mind which is an unſpeakable Reward at preſent. Now of all the Acts of a Rational Soul, <hi>Devotion,</hi> or the Contemplating and Worſhipping of God, brings with it the <hi>Higheſt</hi> Pleaſure; and therefore the Time that is beſtow'd upon it, muſt needs be of the very beſt account.</p>
               <p>The truth of this is, ſuch as Worſhip God with all their Hearts, find by daily Experience the great Pleaſures that go along with their <hi>Acts</hi> of Worſhip; the reliſh and ſatisfaction they leave <hi>behind</hi> upon the Soul, when the Solemnity is <hi>over;</hi> the Delights which <hi>ſtill</hi> accompany the Mind; and the wonderful Comfort and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency wherewith the Day is <hi>Concluded;</hi> theſe <hi>Preſent</hi> Rewards ſhew, that they have well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and husbanded their Time. And when a Man comes at laſt to caſt up his Actions upon his Death-Bed, and to take a true Inventory of them, moſt certainly nothing then can ſpeak greater Peace, or miniſter greater Joy to his departing Soul, than if he be able to give this Teſtimony of himſelf, that amidſt all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies, Vanities, Allurements, and Fatigues of the World, he hath made his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to his Maker.</p>
               <p>This we ſhould conſider in <hi>Time,</hi> and while it is yet called, <hi>To Day.</hi> It becomes Creatures endued with Reaſon, and enlightned with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150153:57"/>
alſo, to <hi>Forecaſt</hi> Events throughly, and to provide ſuch things <hi>Before-hand,</hi> as will ſtand us in good ſtead, and be of ſubſtantial uſe and comfort to us all along; of which, this muſt needs be one of the greateſt and moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; <hi>viz.</hi> A continued <hi>Courſe</hi> of Piety and Religion.</p>
               <p>And what have they to compare with this, who, though they be not <hi>Vicious,</hi> yet are very <hi>Vain</hi> Perſons, <hi>Whiffling</hi> away their hours in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantry and Impertinencies; not as if they were reaſonable Beings, able and obliged to proſecute the nobleſt Ends; but rather little Puppets and Figures of Men, brought into the World, juſt to take a few inſignificant turns in it, and to make a ſhew? Such are thoſe, who know not, or think not how to rid away their time, but by formal Entertainments, by Mirth and Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, by Ceremony and Courtſhip, by idle Viſits, by Finicalneſs in Dreſſing, by Sports and Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; in ſhort, by an unaccountable variety of un-man-like ways of ſpending and paſſing away ones Life. I ſuppoſe ſuch People not formally to <hi>Sin,</hi> but fooliſhly to <hi>Trifle</hi> away their Minutes, which is the ſofteſt and moſt innocent Conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that can be made of it. Now though by theſe mean and childiſh Methods no ſuch Guilt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, as is by down-right Villany and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries; yet this is enough to render them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, that they bring a Man no ſolid ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage or ſatisfaction, and therefore are to be reckoned ſo many loſt Expences. The pleaſure
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150153:58"/>
of them is like an Infant's <hi>Dream,</hi> which is only the preſent Operation of Fancy, that gives him a Minutes Smile. The <hi>Soul</hi> is never awhit the <hi>wiſer,</hi> or <hi>better</hi> for them; but the <hi>worſe</hi> rather, by being degraded from its Dignity, and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliouſly put with all its noble Faculties, to uſes that are ſilly and reproachful. All that can be ſaid of it is, that by the help of theſe mean and trifling ways, ſo much time is gone: The Fool's Fingers are eas'd of it; which will be ſo far from being a comfort to him, that when Sickneſs and Death ſhall come, it will be exceſſive Bitterneſs to conſider, how well ſo many Hours might have been employed, by working out his Salvation in the Church, and in the Cloſet.</p>
               <p>To conclude all: The deſign of this <hi>whole</hi> Diſcourſe is, to ſhew, how much it is our Duty, our Intereſt, and our Wiſdom, to make a good uſe of our Time; and what Courſe is proper for us to take, that it may turn to very good account; to our <hi>Preſent,</hi> and <hi>Future</hi> advantage.</p>
               <p>And would God we would be perſwaded to conſider ſeriouſly, what an <hi>Important</hi> thing this is! the main buſineſs indeed we ſhould be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of in this Life; becauſe it is the <hi>Meaſure</hi> of our Lives; and when Death comes, 'twill be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually as impoſſible to recal the <hi>One,</hi> as it will be again, to live over the <hi>Other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We uſe to call <hi>Time,</hi> the moſt <hi>Precious</hi> thing in the World; and uſe to <hi>Think</hi> it ſuch, when
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150153:58"/>
Matters of great <hi>Conſequence</hi> require quich di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch; in that caſe, a <hi>Day,</hi> an <hi>Hour,</hi> a <hi>Minute</hi> is thought too valuable to be neglected; leſt the Loſs, though but of one <hi>Moment,</hi> ſhould at once defeat the Hopes, and ſpoil all the Labours of an whole <hi>Year.</hi> So that the Improvidence of many People is aſtoniſhing and unaccountable, that when their very <hi>Souls</hi> lie at ſtake, and Hell and Damnation is <hi>before</hi> them, they ſhould then only be <hi>moſt</hi> careleſs of their Time, though the Caſe be of the <hi>Greateſt</hi> Concernment, and the Hazards they run be the moſt <hi>Fatal,</hi> and the Loſs that follows will moſt certainly be utterly <hi>Irreparable</hi> to all <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the truth is, Time is <hi>One</hi> of thoſe <hi>Many</hi> Bleſſings, which Men never ſo <hi>Prize,</hi> as when they <hi>Want</hi> them. The <hi>Sad</hi> Reflexions of a <hi>Death-Bed;</hi> the <hi>Weeping, Wailing, and Gnaſhing of Teeth beyond</hi> it, do plainly argue, that nothing can be more <hi>Worth</hi> recalling, than Time; and nothing more <hi>Worth</hi> our husbanding, than the <hi>Preſent</hi> time; becauſe when once gone, it is <hi>Never</hi> to be recall'd.</p>
               <p>That there may be no room for ſuch <hi>Late</hi> Sorrows, I have laid before you the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and moſt profitable Rules I can think of, how you may employ that time, which is now in your <hi>Hands;</hi> and in a <hi>Moral</hi> ſenſe redeem too what is ſlipt <hi>Away;</hi> as, by Induſtrious Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; by an active and vigorous Repentance; by an operative and univerſal Charity; by caution and watchfulneſs every remaining day of your
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150153:59"/>
Life; and more eſpecially by devoting all the time you can to the Service and Worſhip of God; which of the ſeveral Particulars hath taken up the greateſt ſhare of my Meditations, becauſe it is the Employment of Heaven it ſelf, and that which juſtly claimeth all poſſible Portions of our time here.</p>
               <p>By the diligent performance of theſe things we may ſo redeem our Time, as to make a great deal of a few Days; and do that in one Third of one's Life, which ſome hardly do in their whole Age, though it be a <hi>long</hi> one; and then is a Man's Life to good purpoſe. For 'tis not how <hi>long,</hi> but how <hi>well</hi> a Man lives, which God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders; nor is it his <hi>Years,</hi> but his <hi>Works,</hi> that will be regarded in God's Day. In ſhort: He that exerts all the Faculties and Powers of his Soul in a Courſe of Virtue, and to the utmoſt of his Abilities endeavoues to rectifie what hath been amiſs: He that doth all the Good he can in his Generation, and ſpends not a Day without ſetting forward in ſome meaſure his own and other Men's Salvation; He that gives himſelf to God's Service, and continually makes an Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Heart, and Incenſe of his Prayers; <hi>He</hi> it is that <hi>Redeems</hi> his Time <hi>indeed;</hi> ſo that be it longer or ſhorter, as God ſhall ſee it beſt for him, however he <hi>Began,</hi> he ſhall <hi>Einiſh</hi> his Courſe well: And as <hi>Eliphas</hi> ſaid, <hi>Job</hi> 5. 26. <hi>He ſhall come to his Grave in a full Age, like as a Shock of Corn cometh in,</hi> in his ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb facs="tcp:150153:59"/>
               <head>Morning Prayers.</head>
               <p>O Lord, teach us ſo to number our Days, that we may apply our Hearts unto Wiſdom. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord, ſave us thy Servants, who put our whole Truſt in Thee. Send us Help from thy Holy Place, and evermore mightily defend us. Let the Enemy have no Advantage of us, nor the Wicked approach to us. But be unto us a Strong Tower from the Face of all our Enemies. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord our Heavenly Father, Almighty and Everlaſting God, who haſt ſafely brought us to the Beginning of this Day, defend us in the ſame with thy mighty Power, and grant, that this Day we fall into no Sin, neither run in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any kind of Danger; but that all our Doings may be ordered by thy Governance, to do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that is righteous in thy Sight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God, who knoweſt us to be ſet in the midſt of ſo many and great Dangers,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150153:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150153:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150153:61"/>
that, by reaſon of the Frailty of our Nature, we cannot always ſtand upright; grant to us ſuch Strength and Protection, as may ſupport us in all Dangers, and carry us through all Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty God, who ſeeſt that we have no Power of our ſelves to help our ſelves, keep us, both outwardly in our Bodies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in our Souls; that we may be defended from all Adverſities which may happen to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and from all Evil Thoughts which may aſſault and hurt the Soul, through Cſtriſt our Lord. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty God, who haſt given thine only Son to be unto us both a Sacrifice for Sin, and alſo an Enſample of Godly Life: Give us Grace, that we may always moſt thankfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that his ineſtimable Benefit, and alſo daily endeavour our ſelves to follow the bleſſed Steps of his moſt Holy Life, through the ſame Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Almighty God, who alone canſt order the Unruly Wills and Affections of ſinful Men; Grant unto thy People, that they may love the things which thou commandeſt, and deſire that which thou doſt promiſe; that ſo, among the ſundry and manifold Changes of the World, our Hearts may ſurely there be fixt, where True Joys are to be found, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150153:61"/>
O God, the Protector of all them that truſt in thee, without whom nothing is ſtrong, nothing is holy, increaſe and multiply upon us thy Mercy; that Thou being our Ruler and Guide, we may ſo paſs through things Tenpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that we finally loſe not the things Eternal. Grant this, O Heavenly Father, for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LOrd of all Power and Might, who art the Author and Giver of all Good Things; graft in our Hearts the Love of thy Name; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in us True Religion, nouriſh us with all Goodneſs, and of thy great Mercy keep us in the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>UNto thy Gracious Mercy and Protection, O God, we commit our ſelves. The Lord bleſs us, and keep us. The Lord make his Face to ſhine upon us, and be gracious unto us. The Lord lift up his Countenance upon us, and give us Peace both now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, Hallowed be thy Name, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb facs="tcp:150153:62"/>
               <head>Evening Prayers.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Maker of all things, Judge of all Men; we acknowledge and bewail our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Sins and Wickedneſs, which we from time to time moſt grievouſly have committed, by Thought, Word and Deed, againſt thy Divine Majeſty, provoking moſt juſtly thy Wrath and Indignation againſt us. We do earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and are heartily ſorry for theſe our Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doings; the remembrance of them is grievous unto us, the Burthen of them is intolerable. Have mercy upon us, moſt merciful Father; for thy Son, our Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, forgive us all that is paſt, and grant, that we may ever hereafter ſerve and pleaſe Thee in Newneſs of Life, to the Honour and Glory of thy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LIghten our Darkneſs, we beſeech thee, O Lord, and by thy great Mercy defend us from all Perils and Dangers of this Night, for the Love of thy only Son, our Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150153:62"/>
O Everlaſting God, who haſt ordained and conſtituted the Services of Angels and Men in a wonderful Order; mercifully grant, that as thy Aoly Angels alway do thee Service in Heaven; ſo by thy Appointment they may ſuccour and defend us on Earth, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GRant, O Lord, that as we are Baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Death of thy bleſſed Son, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, Jeſus Chriſt. So by continual mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our corrupt Affections, we may be buried with him, and that through the Grave and Gate of Death we may paſs to our joyful Reſurrection for his Merits, who Died, and was Buried, and Roſe again for us, thy Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, who art always more ready to hear, than we to pray, and are want to give more than either we deſire or deſerve; pour down upon us the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of thy Mercy, forgiving us thoſe things whereof our Conſcience is afraid, and giving us thoſe good things which we are not worthy to ask, but through the Merits and Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt thy Son our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:63"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Printed for, and Sold by,</hi> John Everingham, <hi>at the</hi> Star <hi>in</hi> Ludgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet.</head>
            <p>A Further Enquiry into ſeveral Remarkable Texts of the Old and New Teſtament, which contain ſome Difficulty in them; with a Probable Reſolution of them. By <hi>John Edwards,</hi> B. D. ſometimes Fellow of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Colledge in <hi>Cambridge. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Authority, Stile, and Perfections of the Books of the Old and New Teſtament; with a continued Illuſtration of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral difficult Texts of Scripture throughout the whole Work. By <hi>John Edwards,</hi> Fellow of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Colledge in <hi>Cambridge. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſcellany Eſſays. By Monſieur <hi>St. Eure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont;</hi> with a Character by a Perſon of Honour here in <hi>England.</hi> Continued by Mr. <hi>Dryden.</hi> In Two Volumes. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The True Royal Engliſh School for their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Three Kingdoms; being a Catalogue of all the Words in the Bible. Together with a Praxis in Proſe and Verſes, and Variety of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, all beginning with one Syllable, and proceeding by degrees to Eight, divided and not divided; whereby all Perſons, both Young
<pb facs="tcp:150153:63"/>
and Old, of the meaneſt Abilities, may with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Help be able to read the whole Bible over diſtinctly, eaſily, and more ſpeedily than in any other Method: with Directions to find out any Word. Together with an Expoſition on the Creed. By <hi>Tobias Ellis,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Letters on ſeveral Subjects. By the late Pious Dr. <hi>Henry Moore:</hi> With ſeveral other Letters. To which is added, by the Publiſher, Two Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: One to the Reverend Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dean of St. <hi>Paul's;</hi> and the other to the Reverend Mr. <hi>Bentley:</hi> With other Diſcourſes. Publiſhed by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Elys. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Brief Hiſtory of the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi> call'd alſo <hi>Socinians.</hi> By <hi>Will. Baſſet,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Swithin. London. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commonwealth's-man Unmask'd: Or, a Juſt Rebuke to the Author of the Account of <hi>Denmark.</hi> In Two Parts. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A New Family Book: Or, The True Intereſt of Families: Being Directions to Parents and Children, and to thoſe who are inſtead of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; ſhewing them their ſeveral Duties, and how they may be happy in one another. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſeveral Prayers for Families and Children; and Graces Before and After Meat. To which is Annexed, A Diſcourſe about the Right Way of Improving our Time. By <hi>James Kirkwood,</hi> Rector of <hi>Aſtwick</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> with a Preface by Dr. <hi>Horneck.</hi> The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150153:64"/>
               <hi>Monarchia Microeoſmi;</hi> The Origin, Viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and Periods of Vital Government in Man, for a further Diſcovery of Diſeaſes incident to Humane Nature. By <hi>Everard Maynwaring,</hi> M. D. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gauger and Meaſurer's Companion; being a Compendious Way of Gaging Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies and Solids; with the Reaſons of moſt Multiplications and Diviſions uſed in <hi>Meaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and all difficult Points made plain and eaſie; with a Way to Gage all Quantities under a Gallon. Alſo a Brief Deſcription of the Gage-Point for Ale and Wine Gallons, with Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to find the ſame; and the Contents of a Circle in all its Parts, the exact Method of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring Land, Board, Glaſs, Pavement, Stone, be it of what Form ſoever; together with a Globe and Round Timber, both Decimals and Vulgarly: With Uſeful Tables; a Table of Cylinders, and a Treatiſe of Weights and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. To which is added, at the Requeſt of ſome Gentlemen, a True Method of Brewing Strong Ale in <hi>London,</hi> as well and as good as in any Place in the Country. With Directions for Clarifying any Ale, be it never ſo thick, in few Hours: with Thirty Cuts. By <hi>James Lightbody,</hi> Philomath. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moral Maxims and Reflections. In Four Parts. Written in <hi>French</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefoucault,</hi> and now made <hi>Engliſh. Twelves,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150153:64"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
